<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Protestant plot no paradox, or, Phanaticks under that name plotting against the king and government proved first, from their principles, secondly, from their practices.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10620</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13001898</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13001898</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 396:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Protestant plot no paradox, or, Phanaticks under that name plotting against the king and government proved first, from their principles, secondly, from their practices.</title>
                  <author>Tonge, Thomas, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Graves ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>"An impartial narrative of the indictment, arraignment, tryal and sentence of Thomas Tonge [and 5 others] at Justice-Hall in the Old-Bailey, London, Decemb. 11, 1662": p. 8-29.</note>
                  <note>"The confession, and Francis Stubbs speeches, and prayers of George Phillips, Thomas Tonge, Nathaniel Gibbs, at the place of execution on Munday, Decemb. 22, 1662": p. 29-32.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tonge, Thomas, d. 1662 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Dissenters --  England.</term>
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96473:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96473:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Proteſtant PLOT NO PARADOX: OR, PHANATICKS Under that Name PLOTTING AGAINST THE King and Government.</p>
            <p>PROVED Firſt, From their PRINCIPLES, Secondly, From their PRACTICES.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quo ſemel eſt Imbuta recens ſervabit odorem Teſta diu.</l>
               <l>Tantum religio potuit ſuadere malorum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Graves</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96473:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96473:2"/>
            <head>A Proteſtant Plot NO PARADOX.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are (no doubt) in the world many Honeſt and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable perſons, who themſelves living up to the Rules of the Chriſtian Religion, ſcan the Actions and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of other men by their own, and charitably believe all men are, what by all Laws of Heaven and Earth they ought to be; fearing God, and honouring the King.</p>
            <p>This pious diſpoſition to make and think the beſt, is moſt commendable in every Chriſtian; yet this Charity has its objects, and when miſ-placed, is of dangerous conſequence: <hi>Omnia praeſumuntur bene eſſe facta, donec probetur in contrarium,</hi> is a rule of Law; and yet that Law which preſumes all men (what ſhe intends them for) honeſt, when they appear other, will both take notice of and puniſh them: elſe that which were meant for a curb from Vice, were the greateſt diſpenſation for it. If to think ill too ſoon of men, and upon too ſlight grounds, is uncharitable on the one ſide; to ſhut our eyes againſt the light, and obſtinately to perſiſt in a good opinion of men who by all their actions labour to undeceive us, is as indiſcreet and unſafe on the other. To be tender of the Sheep, is a juſt and neceſſary duty; but to ſpare the Wolf for appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring like one, is the zenith of madneſs, and the very heighth of folly.</p>
            <p>Names make not things, but ſhew them; and forms and appearances alter not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: The Lyon is ſtill a Lyon, though he have the Foxes skin; and the Devil is ſtill the Devil, though he transform himſelf into the appearance of an Angel of light. Men are not <hi>Proteſtants</hi> for calling themſelves ſo; nor does <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> conſiſt in an empty Name: this teaches all men, and obliges all men to <hi>do juſtice and love mercy,</hi> to <hi>fear God and honour the King;</hi> yet there are men, who aſſume to themſelves that Name, that defie the one, and <hi>cum licentia</hi> Murder the other; that are only <hi>juſt</hi> when the ſtrong hand of Law is upon them, and who <hi>love mercy</hi> to the devouring of Widows houſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe men that call themſelves <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and in the ſtile of their late and much-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented Prytomartyr at <hi>Oxford, according to the beſt and pureſt Reformation,</hi> may be Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Murderers; and by their very Principles inclined, I ſay yet more, obliged to be ſo.</p>
            <p>And this is a ſad truth, fit for every man to know, notwithſtanding ſo many Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Letters and Papers with ſo great labour and art ſent abroad of late to perſwade the contrary. And if the Proteſtant Plot, (for ſo the Phanaticks would have us believe) may be an invention of the Papiſts, to draw us from a further enquiry into their own now almoſt deſperate one; 'tis not impoſſible, but ſo many late Pamphlets, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a poſſibility of a Proteſtant Plot, are by theſe as cunningly ſpread abroad, to work the Government into a fatal ſecurity, by a new-created confidence of their Loyalty.</p>
            <p>The old ſerpent has for many years, with two great Batteries, aſſaulted the Church of <hi>England, Popery</hi> and <hi>Phanaticiſm;</hi> the firſt his eldeſt iſſue, but the latter the more hopeful and active. Long had the firſt been making his approach with ſmall ſucceſs, when the latter ſoon, and like a true Devil, almoſt inviſibly made a mighty breach, which all the valour and skill of the Defenders could not make good.</p>
            <p>Here it will not be amiſs to take things a little higher, and ſhew, how theſe two migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtreams, which ſeem to take two ways, and are in appearance ſo contrary, have yet one ſpring, are indeed the ſame, and tend to the ſame end.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96473:3"/>
            <p>The Prince of darkneſs and of this world, inraged at his repulſe in the perſon of the great Redeemer of Mankind, and deſperately mad to ſee all his labours defeated, and his hopes in his old Rebel the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> confounded by the obedience and ſacrifice of the ſecond, reſolved to try if he could be more fortunate in his offers to ſome one who were merely Man.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Conclave, and its monſtrous Head the Pope, were pitcht upon; to theſe he renews the offers of all the Kingdoms of the world and their glory, if ſo be falling down, they would worſhip him. Scarce was the offer made, but accepted; nay, more was paid than promiſed: for they not only worſhipped him themſelves, but drew the world after them to do ſo too; for which the grateful Devil was better than his word, and to all the Kingdoms of this world in poſſeſſion, granted them in reverſion his other in the next.</p>
            <p>Under this Title, and for ought I know the beſt they have, they claimed the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the world; but wanting force to make good their claim, they a while diſſembled their pretenſions, confining their Authority to a Spiritual Kingdom, till by degrees they workt themſelves into the Temporal one too, and arrived to that prodigious pitch of greatneſs we this day behold them at.</p>
            <p>Twice four hundred years was the <hi>Chriſtian Iſrael</hi> in bondage to this <hi>Spiritual Egypt,</hi> when at laſt God was pleaſed to deliver them, and bring them again into the right Worſhip of himſelf, whoſe ſervice is perfect freedom. <hi>England</hi> began to perceive the madneſs of enſlaying Soul and Body to a Forreign Juriſdiction, of ſacrificing the one, and much endangering the other, to ſatisfie the Pride, Luxury and Ambition of a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; reſolved to be free, and was ſo: ſince which time, the reſtleſs malice of <hi>Rome</hi> has not ceaſed her continual endeavours to reſtore her loſt Authority in this Kingdom, and re-unite ſo ſweet a Province to her Empire.</p>
            <p>Long like a gallant enemy ſhe waged fair and open War, which ſerved but to make us ſtand the better on our guard; <hi>forewarned, forearmed:</hi> ſtill their deſigns failed, and their Counſels were brought to nought, till almoſt deſpairing, they were giving over the Cauſe; when the Devil, who ſtill helps his ſervants at a dead lift, ſent them an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected relief: in ſtept the very worſt Order of men, the moſt fruitful in invention, the moſt forward in execution of all villany, the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> whoſe Name is <hi>Legion,</hi> for <hi>many</hi> Devils are in him.</p>
            <p>Theſe inſtruments of Hell, of the Devils own making, ſoon changed the face of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; <hi>Divide &amp; impera</hi> was their Motto: what cannot be beaten down, muſt be blown up: a little Diſſention within, helps more, than a mighty Army without: theſe new Maxims produced new Counſels, and thoſe Counſels put them upon taking new mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and the deep policy of the Jeſuite juſtly admired by the Conclave, entitled him to the chief adminiſtration of Affairs.</p>
            <p>Now, and not till now, were the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at a loſs: for whereas hitherto they had hung out their own Colours, ſo that we had time at a diſtance to diſcover and know our enemy, and prepare for our defence; theſe were taken in, they manned out Engliſh Bottoms, and Engliſh Colours were ſet up, whereby, not ſuſpected by us, we were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized by them; and if after a ſharp diſpute we had the good luck to get clear of them, yet we were very much battered and diſabled.</p>
            <p>Well knew the ſubtle Jeſuite, that Popery and its Principles (by the remembrance of <hi>Smith-field-fires,</hi> and thoſe other prodigious villanies and cruelties in the <hi>Quinquennium Mariae</hi>) were the averſion of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and that many good and wholſome Laws, like ſo many well-mann'd Outworks, forbid the approach to our walls: wherefore giving over aſſaulting us without, they wrought underhand within, corrupted the Guards, gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Walls, and turned the Cannon upon us; and now when by the treachery and baſeneſs of thoſe whom we truſted, the enemy was got on ſo far, that the very means of our ſafety became the inſtruments of our deſtruction, what could be expected but that which followed? the Governour was Murdered, the chief Commanders killed or impriſoned, and the Common Souldiers forced to ſerve the conquering and prevailing Party. And thus what the united Arms Spiritual and Temporal of <hi>Rome</hi> could not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; what the formidable power of <hi>Spain,</hi> then the Monarch of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the <hi>Indies</hi> Lord, to their loſs and confuſion attempted in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days; what the ſecret Conſpiracies of Papiſts failed of compaſſing in her Succeſſor's, that a few falſe brethren, acting by the ſame Principles, under different appellations, brought to paſs in the days of the late King; who as in his troubles he at leaſt equall'd <hi>David,</hi> ſo might he well ſay with him, <hi>For 'twas not an open enemy that did me this diſhonour, for then I could have born it, neither was it mine adverſary that did magnifie himſelf againſt me, for then peradventure
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96473:3"/> I would have hid my ſelf from him: but is was even thou my companion, my guide and my own familiar friend; we took ſweet Counſel together, and walked in the houſe of God as friends.</hi> A ſtratagem of War well known to the Phanatick, to draw the Defenders (more valiant than wiſe) by a falſe Alarum of an intended aſſault by the Papiſts to one ſide, whilſt the Town was ſurprized, and truly taken by themſelves on the other. So much more dangerous is a falſe friend, than a fair foe.</p>
            <p>And all this is done not in a humour, or by accident (for then we might comfort our ſelves with the hope that it would happen no more) but deſignedly, upon principles of Conſcience and Religion; <hi>Their Prophets propheſie falſe things, and the people love to have it ſo;</hi> they <hi>compaſs Sea and Land to make a Proſelyte, and when he is made,</hi> they make him <hi>twofold more the Child of Hell than themſelves:</hi> for <hi>there is no faithfulneſs in their mouth, their inward parts are very wickedneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To run over all their Anti-monarchick Principles, were an endleſs task; I ſhall pick out one, which comprehends all the reſt. <hi>The Original power of Kings they place in, and derive from the People, to which, as Rivers to their mother Ocean, it ought to return again, when the end for which Kings have been entruſted, their</hi> ſalus populi, <hi>is by themſelves apprehended not ſo well provided for, as by ſome other conſtitution of Government in their opinion it might be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Principle is either true or falſe: If true, it is impoſſible for any people ever to Rebel; for Rebellion muſt ſtill be againſt the Supreme Authority, which is lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this Rule in themſelves. If falſe, it is almoſt as impoſſible, upon every diſlike or fancy that comes upon them, for them not to do ſo: for it is ridiculous to imagine, that a people conceiving themſelves oppreſt, ſhould not make uſe of their power, when they are taught to believe it rightful, to fight themſelves into Liberty.</p>
            <p>Infinite are the ill conſequences of this one Principle; this alone warrants all the evils of the late Civil War, this juſtifies the Parliaments taking up Arms againſt the King: by this, the Kingly power ſtruck ſtill on the peoples ſide; this divided his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from his Authority, and when the firſt was at <hi>York,</hi> made the other their Priſoner at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> this makes out that part of his monſtrous charge, <hi>That the King can commit Treaſon.</hi> Laſtly, This made out the <hi>major ſingulis, minor univerſis;</hi> which autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized (as they ſay) their proceedings in his Tryal, and warranted the Sentence of our modern <hi>Pontius-Pilate,</hi> the greater villain of the two, in many reſpects; the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing a lawful Authority, though in an ill cauſe; this an Arbitrary power upon one over whom he neither had nor could have any Authority: a Heathen and a ſtranger had more bowels for a Jew, in that caſe, than a Reformed Chriſtian for his King, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen in this: neither in the laſt day, when he ſhall know what it is to judge a King, and ſlay the Anointed of the Lord, ſhall he have this to offer in mitigation of his Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that like the other, (who upon a bare ſurmiſe that he was a King, though he indeed knew <hi>no King but Caeſar</hi>) he ſought to <hi>let him go,</hi> whom he knew well to be the King, and could not but know, that <hi>through envy they had delivered him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if theſe men ſtill retain and profeſs this and the like Principles, why ſhould it be ſo unreaſonable for their Governours by all juſt ways to provide againſt the like pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices? <hi>Ictus piſcator ſapit;</hi> he that having once felt the flame, will again expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if he be burnt will fall unpitied.</p>
            <p>But they may ſay, Why are theſe things, which by the mercy of our King have been forgiven, caſt again in our diſh? is there not an Act of Oblivion which ſtands betwixt them &amp; us? is there any thing of later date to that, to riſe in judgment againſt us? do we not live peaceably with our Neighbours, &amp; in all due ſubmiſſion to the Kings Laws?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer: Men that deſign diſturbance in, and an alteration of Government, do accordingly take their meaſures; and whilſt ſecretly they Cabal, Project, and take Counſel for War, Ruine and Confuſion, are outwardly, and in ſhew, the greateſt promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Peace, Charity, good Order, and Obedience, till their Counſels are ripe for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And we have the more reaſon to fear ſome ſuch deſign now on foot, becauſe we find the ſame Principles as occaſioned the laſt Rebellion, are with great care new vented in many Pamphlets lately come out, and are as generally received, applauded, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the ſame ſort of men. Of this, amongſt many others, a late celebrated Piece, the <hi>No Proteſtant Plot,</hi> is a proof; in which the Author labours, from the Principles of Religion, to prove the impoſſibility of a Proteſtant Plot. Take it in his own words, See <hi>Proteſt. Plot firſt part, p.</hi> 7. <hi>To charge a Conſpiracy upon Proteſtants againſt the King, is to ſuppoſe them Fools as well as Traytors,</hi> (what news he tells us! why every man that means to become a Traytor, is at the ſame time neceſſarily a Fool, if we conſider what he is to expect if he miſcarry here, if otherwiſe hereafter) <hi>for had they no regard</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96473:4"/> our Author) <hi>to the obligations of Conſcience, yet the reſpect which they muſt be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended to bear to their own ſafety, will compel them, if they have any love for themſelves, to be loyal to his Majeſty.</hi> That is, <hi>ſeldome comes a better;</hi> they know not how at preſent to mend themſelves, and therefore for once are content to bear with him. And that this is plainly his meaning, appears from that which follows: for ſays he, <hi>As matters one ſtated at this day in the world, they muſt forfeit their Reaſon, before they can abandon their Allegiance.</hi> So that it ſeems the Saints have their <hi>times,</hi> when they may be Rebels up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>good reaſon:</hi> and yet the reſult of all is but this, that <hi>at this time we cannot reaſonably ſuppoſe a Proteſtant Plot;</hi> which very conceſſion is againſt them: for taking that <hi>pro con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſo,</hi> it is neither any <hi>principle of Religion,</hi> or <hi>obligation of Conſcience,</hi> but the <hi>circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the time,</hi> that admit not of a Plot.</p>
            <p>And then what a condition is the King in! what reaſon can he have to truſt men who have already once deceived him, and do as good as tell him would do again, were they not more reſtrained by fear of the Succeſſor to, than any ſence of Duty, principle of Loyalty, or affection to the poſſeſſor of the Crown: yet even this were ſome ground for a preſent ſecurity, if it were true; but there is nothing leſs ſo, than the aſſerted reaſon of the preſent Loyalty. Heretofore indeed, when men upon ſome civil pretence compaſſed the death of a King, their malice &amp; miſchief went not further than his perſon; and though the Governour fell, the Government was preſerved: but ſince men have Rebelled upon a <hi>Religious account,</hi> the miſchief goes a great deal farther. Of inſtances, though Hiſtory be full, two ſhall ſuffice; great ones indeed, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>French League,</hi> and <hi>Scotch Covenant.</hi> In the firſt, the blood of one King was no allay to the ſanctified zeal of the <hi>Guyzards; H.</hi> 3. fell, but the war was continued with greater height than ever againſt his Succeſſor <hi>H.</hi> ſurnamed the Great, upon the ſcore of Religion now; with whom they meant to have diſſolved that Monarchy, and have cantoned the Kingdom. The other deadly inſtance is too well known; and 'tis very plain from all the events and actions in that War, 'twas not only the King, but the Kingly Office they fought againſt: the Saints are thorough Reformers, and go through-ſtich: when a King by them is Murdered, the very Foundations of Government are overthrown; and 'tis made Treaſon to aſſert, (what it would be ſo now to deny) the Supreme Authority in a ſingle perſon. And I doubt not but the Saints of our time would come up to the great example of their renowned Anceſtors; they ſeem to plot for a ſingle life, though a Royal one; all that pretend that way, muſt periſh or ſave their lives by falling down and worſhipping Common-wealth; that <hi>Golden Image</hi> which the Saints once did, and would again <hi>ſet up.</hi> He is a took, that believes that they who having Murdered the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſet the Head of the Son to ſale, would, ſhould they Murder the Son, have more Kindneſs for his Brother; or that <hi>James</hi> D. of <hi>Y.</hi> ſhould eſcape better, when <hi>Ch.</hi> the Second were killed, than the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> ſhould, had they caught him upon the Murder of <hi>Ch.</hi> the Firſt.</p>
            <p>But to return to our Author; he tells us of another tye, <hi>Obligations of Conſcience;</hi> and no doubt theſe ſhould make men honeſt. But how far Conſcience is binding in a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick, is worth enquiry; and I find it reſolved to my hand, in his Second Part of the <hi>No Proteſtant Plot,</hi> pag. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where Allegiance is tyed to Intereſt,</hi> I know it will change as that does: but Conſcience ſhould be always the ſame; and yet a true Proteſtant Conſcience is not ſo: for our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſays, <hi>That 'tis poſſible for a Prince to cancel all bonds by which Subjects are tyed to him:</hi> and gives for inſtance wherein, <hi>viz. his excluding a company of innocent perſons from the benefit and protection of the Law;</hi> for this, he aſſures us, <hi>deſtroys all pleas and arguments which may influence their Conſciences to obedience:</hi> that is, they are no longer obliged to be obedient to a Governour, than they are the better for him: ſo that indeed, the Kings Conſcience, and not their own, is the ſtandard of their Allegiance.</p>
            <p>Is this to <hi>be ſubject for Conſcience ſake?</hi> I would be thankful to any man that would reconcile the Doctrine of theſe Proteſtants with that of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> but they ſay, it needs not; 'tis an old antiquated concluſion drawn from a propoſition not admitted by them. <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> (there they hold with him:) <hi>whether to the King as ſupreme;</hi> there <hi>Paul</hi> was a <hi>Tory,</hi> and now they differ: for <hi>the powers that are,</hi> ſays that Apoſtle, of Nations, ſpeaking ſtill of Kings, <hi>are ordained of God:</hi> we deny the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, they are made by the peole. Now 'tis no wonder if denying the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they reject the Concluſion; a pretty indulgence that for Rebellion; nay, it places in the People, without appeal from them, the right of determining when the King for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits his Crown. And can any man after this, with modeſty pretend, that 'tis ſo very hard, ſo morally impoſſible, for men holding theſe Principles to be Rebels, when by them, as I ſaid at firſt, he is in ſome ſort obliged to be ſo?</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96473:4"/>
            <p>And that theſe are their Principles, any man without much argument thay be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to believe, that will take the pains to enquire into and obſerve their Practice, in all times within theſe forty years. There has been a <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> we are ſure of that, and if conſpiring the Death of the King; and the Subverſion of the Government, be a Plot, and Fanaticks be Proteſtants, I find at leaſt Three Proteſtant Plots within that time. From Forty One, to 1660, I think may paſs for one; <hi>Venner</hi> and his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions for a Second; that of that of 1662. of which more hereafter, for a third; and to make good meaſure, let that in <hi>April</hi> 1666. be added. Of theſe two laſt there is extant an account: but becauſe the firſt of theſe, for many reaſons is by much the more remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I have at the end here added the whole proceedings againſt thoſe Criminals, as the ſame were exactly taken by the ſame, Gentleman who took and afterwards printed the Trial of the late Kings Regicides. The reading of this Tryal, is alone ſufficient to convince all ſober and judicious men, that theſe practious are very natural, and ſuitable to the Principles they flow from. Out of Which I have gathered ſome obſervations, as they affect the preſent time; and do here ſet them down firſt, that the Reader having ſome light into the Tryal, may the better weigh the greatneſs of the villany and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief that was intended.</p>
            <p>But the Fanatick perhaps may object the uncharitableneſs of charging the ſins of a few perſons upon a whole party. To this I anſwer, <hi>When thou ſawedſt a Thief, thou conſentedſt unto him.</hi> Nor was this the product of a few mens brains; as anon it will appear. But how does it appear (will they ſay) that theſe men here convicted were Fanaticks? '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is true indeed, the Religion of the individual perſons cannot be ſo far made out, as to point to the particular Sect and Opinion of each, ſince moſt of them were ſilent at their deaths as to that; and he of them that did ſpeak, tells us rather what he is not, than what he is; for the ſame reaſon poſſibly with a late Brother in the like circumſtances at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that the blame and odium of their Crimes might not fall upon their Party. Yet thus far without doubt we may venture, from their employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the late Civil War, their affections to the King, Lawn ſleeves, and Circingle, to conclude, that men ſo uneaſie-under, and ſo ſoon weary of Monarchy; ſo little ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with, and ſo ill affected to Hierarchy, had not their education in, nor ever were Members of that which alone deſerves <hi>the glorious Sirname of true Proteſtant,</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> by Law eſtabliſht.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe pretty plain, they were not Papiſts, further than all Sectaries are indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ſo, being all ſeveral iſſue of that common Mother.</p>
            <p>It remains then that they muſt be <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> Diſſenters indeed, and as much divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their Tenets from each other, as they are all from the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters ih every thing, but their old malice and continued Plots againſt her; in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring whoſe overthrow, (though no two of them agree among themſelves) they are all of a piece; to this they can give unfeignedly <hi>aſſent and conſent;</hi> ſo very forward in this ther zeal, that they always reſolve of pulling down the one, before ever they once conſider of ſetting up any other.</p>
            <p>This was a Plot indeed, that ſhewed the Authors Maſters in their Myſtery; a general Plot; not a few hot-brain'd fools met together without Order or Diſcipline, Friends or Money; but a cloſe and deep contrivance formed after long deliberation; things well weighed and digeſted; every man his particular Province aſſigned, and every Sect (not one excepted) engaged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all intereſts were agreed, <hi>Fifth Monarchy men, Anabaptiſts; Independents, Fighting Quakers;</hi> and the <hi>Congregational Churches</hi> were conſenting; and the <hi>Preſbyterian,</hi> (that firſt-born of Rebellion) though not ſo viſibly at the head as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſes, yet full as deep as any; and if he craftily pulled in his horns in appearance, 'twas but to play the villain with more ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Yet ſome good honeſt harmleſs well-meaning men, may perhaps miſtake this policy for honeſty, and imagine remorſe of Conſcience for former offences, or a grateful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of an Act of Oblivion, occaſioned it; but for my part, I have not Charity enough to believe, that they can either repent indeed of old ſins, or forbear attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting new ones, when occaſion offers itſelf. <hi>Naturam expellas fureâ licet uſque, recurret.</hi> Can a Black be waſht white? <hi>or do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thiſtles?</hi> They were not grown honeſter, but wiſer, (if cunning in miſchief, improved by long practice, may deſerve that name:) they yet remembred how in the late Rebellion, they had born the heat and burthen of the day, and how yet thoſe that came in at the eleventh hour were made not equal, but ſuperiour to them: they had been the firſt aggreſſors, at a vaſt expence of Blood and Treaſure; when the <hi>Independent</hi> ſtept in, tript up their heels, reaped the fruit of their labours, and even ſurfeited with the riches of their ſpoils their
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:96473:5"/> Blood had paid for; their birthright not bought, but forced from them, and not a ſingle meſs left them to feed on: <hi>Virgil</hi>'s fate was theirs; <hi>Hanc ego rempublicam feci, tulit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honores:</hi> they were therefore now for playing an after-game, and deſired in their turn to be even with their younger brother; by which means, nothing venturing, they had hopes of all; to ſtep into the Government if the Plot ſucceeded, to ſlip out of the halter if it miſcarried.</p>
            <p>For your <hi>true Proteſtant Diſſenter,</hi> whoſe Province is Rebellion, hates no Plot but that which miſcarries; <hi>proſperum ſcelus vocatur virtus;</hi> and is as proud to own a ſucceſsful villany, as cunning to ſhift it when 'tis not ſo. So when lately God for unſcrutable cauſes was pleaſed to proſper the Arms of Traytors againſt their lawful Sovereign, how forward, (even to ambition) were they of being eſteemed the Patrons of that then glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious villany? <hi>Keepers of the Liberties of</hi> England, <hi>Godly reforming Saints,</hi> and what elſe were they not? but when in proceſs of time, by as many ſudden and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry revolutions as any Age or Hiſtory can boaſt of, his Majeſty was reſtored, and the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and thorough Reformation was ſolemnly damn'd, and declared a downright deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Rebellion; not a Saint had a hand in it then; 'twas a damn'd Popiſh Plot, deviſed to diſcredit the Kings Proteſtant Subjects; and every babe was taught to anſwer to ſo much of his Catechiſm, <hi>That the Papiſts cut off the Kings Head;</hi> an evaſion poor, even to ridiculouſneſs, That the Papiſts ſhould raiſe and carry on a War againſt Popery: for that was then (as ſtill it is) the burthen of the Song. But a ſorry ſhift is better than none.</p>
            <p>That relation of Dr. <hi>du Moulin</hi> of diſguiſed Jeſuits ſent over by the French Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, which they urge ſo often in their own excuſe, does not at all ſhift the Scene; an account that makes (in my opinion) much againſt them; it proves them Fools as well as Knaves; derogating much from their policy, without the leaſt addition to their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty: For if a Jeſuit ſuitably habited, may paſs for a zealous holder-forth, and that they look no farther; then the outſide of a man, a ſtarcht Band, a brace of Caps, a whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Tone, ſome ſix Grymaces, with as many Crocodile Tears, are all the ingredients that go to the making up a painful Soul-ſaving Preacher.</p>
            <p>For they try not the ſpirits that are amongſt them, digeſting every thing with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite Faith; know no more of a man than his habit; and ſeem not to have read, or altogether to have forgotten, that <hi>a tree is known by its fruit,</hi> and men by their <hi>works,</hi> not <hi>habits;</hi> that <hi>ravenous Wolves</hi> are then moſt dangerous, when they appear in <hi>ſheeps cloathing.</hi> If then <hi>Diſſenters</hi> may be thus impoſed upon; if where there is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, there will be a Jeſuit, that is, a villain; which may by no means be queſtioned, it having the authority of a man whoſe Evidence has ſtood the Teſt of Three Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and of which a freſh inſtance we have in the perſon of the Doctor: if ſo it be; and that the moſt pernicious matter in point of Doctrine may be diſguized by the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous but moſt affected manner of delivering it, ſo as to paſs currant; a man may I hope conclude, and his hair never ſtand an end for the matter, that it is no ſuch Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, nor monſtrous abſurdity,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>this ſort of Proteſtants,</hi> but moſt <hi>unprimitive Chriſtians,</hi> may be, and are, by their very Principles, engaged in Plots and Deſigns againſt the King and his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. One may believe without offence, that 'tis day, when the Sun ſhines; and we may conclude from all that we have ſeen, read, and known of theſe men, that their practice did never belye their Principles; and this more particularly will appear in the following Tryal.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That not only ſome few individual perſons (though ſuch only can be made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples) but whole Sects and Parties, and to uſe their own cant, their very Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Churches, may be aiding and conſenting to, and actually engaged in Treaſonable Deſigns; of which this Tryal is an undeniable evidence. Here the Reader will find their <hi>grand Councels of Forty, Councels of Six; Committees of Secrecy, general Officers, Agents, Collectors, Treaſurers, Magazines, Arms and Ammunition.</hi> Upon which, this is obſervable, that though it be not extraordinary for two or three men, without confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or putting their heads together, by accident to jump in the ſame thought, fancy, or deſign; yet where-ever all the ſeveral Sects of <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> and all the great perſons in every Sect, take the ſame reſolutions at the ſame time, ſo ſtrait and general an Union muſt of neceſſity proceed from ſome one principle that is common to them all; it being full as unlikely, and as unreaſonable to ſuppoſe ſo ſtrange a conjunction ſhould be by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as to imagine that a handful of ſand thrown into the air, ſhould in falling to the ground form a perfect page in <hi>Homer</hi> or <hi>Virgil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96473:5"/>4. Another thing obſervable from this Tryal, is, That <hi>Sham-plots</hi> are not ſo late an invention as ſome pretend; and if (as they ſay) the Papiſts under colour of a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Plot, meant more ſecurely to compaſs their own, I can tell them in what School they learnt that craft; of the Fanatick, the elder Brother for <hi>Shams</hi> of the two, who having cunningly ſpread a rumour of an intended Maſſacre by the Papiſts, deſigned themſelves, under the ſecurity of that report, to cut off all, from the <hi>Cedar</hi> down to the <hi>Hyſope:</hi> ſo that 'tis no new thing for Fanaticks to be Murderers and Rebels, and throw it upon the Papiſts. A bloody purpoſe it was, a villany as much exceeding the Iriſh Maſſacre, as the Proteſtants of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> do thoſe of <hi>Ireland</hi> in number; beſides the dignity of one above the reſt, and more worth than all the reſt, the King.</p>
            <p>There is another conſideration, that incrceaſes that guilt above the others, by how much they pretend to be better Chriſtians, and better principled. Neither was their <hi>Sham</hi> upon the Papiſts only; 'twas upon the King himſelf: for by that Letter in the Tryal it appears, the Kings Guards were that Popiſh Army that was kept on foot to do ſuch mighty things. And at that rate, what do theſe men make of the King, who keeps and pays that Army, but a Murderer and a Papiſt?</p>
            <p>But here I would not be miſconſtrued, as if I deſigned to clear the Romaniſts from thoſe ſins, but I would <hi>give</hi> (as the ſaying is) <hi>the Devil his due,</hi> and ſet every ſaddle upon the right horſe: they have more than enough to do to clear themſelves of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notorious principles, diſpenſing with, and encouraging Treaſons and Maſſacres, the ſad effects whereof are yet felt in ſome, and remembred in moſt Kingdoms of <hi>Europe;</hi> ſo that they cannot want Preſidents of their own, without borrowing of the Fanaticks, who indeed have enough and to ſpare.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By the Letter I mentioned but now, and which the Reader will find in the Tryal, it appears, that your true Proteſtant Diſſenting Conſcience has a diſpenſation for Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too, and in the very ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of a Jeſuit, call God to witneſs in the moſt ſolemn man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if they were <hi>as innocent as the Child unborn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if the principles of Pope and Presbyter are ſo near akin; if it be ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral for the firſt to be Plotting, how comes it to be ſo almoſt impoſſible at any, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together impoſſible at this time, for the latter to be ſo too? and ſurely for any number of men (whatſoever their authority may be as a Grand Enqueſt) upon the ſingle, poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and obſtinate preſumption of the principles of theſe Proteſtants, right or wrong to return <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> is not perhaps the cleareſt Evidence of a truly tender and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Conſcience. And this by way of caution I ſhall add, That ſince Juries have found Bills of High-Treaſon againſt <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and ſuch as call themſelves <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and are in nothing ſo but the Name; the late ſtrange deliverance of ſome, is not a ſufficient ground for that aſſurance and freedom with which ſome men ſpeak, and almoſt act whatſoever they pleaſe: ſo great a ſecurity in confidence of an <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> may in time prove fatal.</p>
            <p>And now having ſeen the Principles of theſe men, I conceive it by this time plain, that they may Plot; and from this following Tryal, which is matter of fact freſh in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, and for truth unqueſtionable, it is as plain they do. To endeavour to make it out yet more plainly, were loſt labour: for them whom the following Tryal ſhall not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, it is impoſſible ever to convince by any Arguments. As deep a piece of villany it contains, as ever was intended to have been acted on any ſtage; and had it taken ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, it had been as general a deſolation: and I think, that conſidering the perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring, and the perſons conſpired againſt, and the pretence of the Conſpiracy, <hi>Religion;</hi> any ordinary judgment muſt needs agree, that that muſt needs be a very ſcurvy Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which infuſes ſuch Principles into men, as will not let them live quietly under any Government; who will own no Authority above their own; conſider the King as their Tenant at will; and eſteem <hi>ſubjection for Conſcience ſake,</hi> a Doctrine for ſlaves, Turks, Vaſſals, and French Boors: a people not to be encouraged, becauſe not to be relyed on; whom neither the King, who is all Mercy; nor the Law, that is the ſtricteſt Juſtice; the favour of the one, nor rigour of the other, can reclaim, and contain within the bounds of duty; whom neither the powers of this world, nor the conſideration of the next, no Ordinance of God or man, can make honeſt; who will neither obey for <hi>love</hi> nor <hi>fear;</hi> and be ſubject neither for <hi>wrath</hi> nor <hi>for conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="court_proceedings">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96473:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>An Impartial Narrative of the Indictment, Arraignment, Tryal and Sentence of</hi> Thomas Tonge, George Phillips, Francis Stubbs, James Hind, John Sallers, <hi>and</hi> Nathaniel Gibbs, <hi>at</hi> Juſtice-Hall <hi>in the</hi> Old-Bailey, London, Decemb. 11. 1662.</head>
               <p>THE Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> being read, and Proclamation made, the Grand-Jury were ſworn, whoſe Names are,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arthur Jourdan,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Freeſtone,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Fawſon,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Coney,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Compere,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iſaac Rutter,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chr. Rigby,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rowland Steed,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Standen,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Worth,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Rigby,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leonard Staples.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeveral Witneſſes being called, there appeared <hi>William Hill, Edward Rigg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Tyler, Godolphin, Bonfoy,</hi> and ſeveral others; who being all ſworn, were directed up to the Grand-Jury.</p>
               <p>After ſome hours examination of the Witneſſes, and conſultation, the Grand-Jury returned the Indictment <hi>Billa vera.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>You good men of the City of <hi>London,</hi> ſummoned to appear here this day, to enquire between our Soveraign Lord the King, and the Priſoners that are and ſhall be at the Bar, anſwer to your Names as you ſhall be called, every one at their firſt Call, upon pain and peril that ſhall fall thereon. Good men of the Ward of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>Serjeant <hi>Glyn,</hi> Sergeant <hi>Maynard,</hi> His Majeſties Serjeants at Law, Sir <hi>Jeoffry Palmer</hi> Attorney-General, Sir <hi>Heneage Finch</hi> His Majeſties Sollicitor, Serjeant <hi>Keeling</hi> His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Serjeant, Sir <hi>Edward Turnor,</hi> taking their places in Court, the Priſoners were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be ſet to the Bar.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Tonge,</hi> hold up thy hand; <hi>George Phillips,</hi> hold up thy hand; <hi>Francis Stubbs,</hi> hold up thy hand; <hi>James Hinde,</hi> hold up thy hand; <hi>John Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> hold up thy hand; and <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs,</hi> hold up thy hand. Which they ſeverally doing, their Indictment was read, the ſubſtance whereof is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>YOU the Priſoners that were laſt called to the Bar, ſtand Indicted in <hi>London</hi> by the Names of <hi>Thomas Tonge,</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Diſtiller; <hi>George Phillips,</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Yeoman; <hi>Francis Stubbs,</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Cheeſe-monger; <hi>James Hind,</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Gunner; <hi>John Sallers,</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Compaſs-maker; and <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs,</hi> late of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Felt-maker, for that you ſix, together with divers others particularly in the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mentioned, and others not yet taken, as falſe Traytors to the Illuſtrious, Serene, and moſt Excellent Prince <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, by the Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> King, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> minding, and with all their force intending the Peace and Tranquillity of this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> to diſturb, and our ſaid Soveraign Lord the King to death and final deſtruction to bring and put, the 31. day of <hi>October,</hi> in the Fourteenth year of the Reign of our ſaid Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, Traiterouſly did compaſs, imagine and Intend the killing of our ſaid Soveraign Lord the King, and the antient Government of this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> to change [as in the Indictment more particularly was mentioned.]</p>
                  <p>What ſayeſt thou <hi>Thomas Tonge,</hi> art thou guilty of this High-Treaſon in manner and form as thou ſtandeſt Indicted, or not guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>Not guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>How wilt thou be Tryed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>By God and my Countrey.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſayeſt thou <hi>George Phillips,</hi> art thou guilty? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phill.</speaker>
                  <p>I am guilty in hearing and not diſcovering of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>Art thou guilty of this High-Treaſon whereof thou ſtandect Indicted?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phill.</speaker>
                  <p>I am guilty, but not in manner and form as I ſtand Indicted; I have heard the words, as I formely confeſſed to Sir <hi>Richard Brown:</hi> not guilty as to the manner and form.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>How wilt thou be Tryed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phill.</speaker>
                  <p>By God and my Countrey.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſayeſt thou <hi>Francis Stubbs,</hi> art thou guilty? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stub.</speaker>
                  <p>Not guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96473:6"/>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>How wilt thou be Tryed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stub.</speaker>
                  <p>By God and my Countrey.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſayeſt thou <hi>James Hind,</hi> art thou guilty? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hind</hi> kneeling down, and diſcovering much penitency, anſwered, I am guilty, and humbly beg mercy of His Majeſty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Record his Confeſſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſayeſt thou <hi>John Sallers,</hi> art thou guilty? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sall.</speaker>
                  <p>Not guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>How wilt thou be Tryed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sall.</speaker>
                  <p>By God and the Countrey.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſayeſt thou <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs,</hi> art thou guilty? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>Not guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
                  <p>How wilt thou be Tryed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>By God and the Countrey.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Carry up <hi>Hind</hi> to the Gaole. And the reſt ſtanding at the Bar, ſilence was commanded.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Tonge, George Phillips, Francis Stubbs, John Sallers,</hi> and <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs;</hi> You the Priſoners that were laſt called to the Bar, thoſe men that you ſhall hear called, are to paſs upon Tryal for your ſeveral Lives and Deaths; if you, or any of you will challenge them or any of them, you muſt challenge them when they come to the Book to be Sworn, before they be Sworn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edmond Butler.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tonge.</hi> I challenge him; but afterwards admitted him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Edmund Butler, Clement Punge, George Dixon, Samuel Pain, John Bagnal, John Gourney, William Gayler, Ralph Silverton, William Dudley, Joſeph Drake, John Peake,</hi> and <hi>Robert Morrice</hi> were ſeverally Sworn in this manner: Lay your hand on the Book, look upon the Priſoners: You ſhall well and truly try, and true deliverance make between our Soveraign Lord the King and the Priſoners at the Bar, whom you ſhall have in charge according to your Evidence. So help you God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>Count theſe, <hi>Cryer, Edmond Butler; Cryer,</hi> one; <hi>Clement Punge,</hi> two, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Twelve good men and true, ſtand together and hear your Evidence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cryer,</hi> make Proclamation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cryer.</speaker>
                  <p>O Yes, If any one can inform my Lords the Kings Juſtices, the Kings Serjeants, or the Kings Attorney, before this Inqueſt be taken, let them come forth and they ſhall be heard; for now the Priſoners ſtand at the Bar upon their Deliverance; and all others that are bound by Recognizance to give Evidence againſt any of the Priſoners at the Bar, come forth and give Evidence, or elſe you forfeit your Recognizance: and all manner of perſons that were ſummoned upon the Jury, and have not yet been Sworn, they are diſcharged, and may depart the Court.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tho. Tonge,</hi> Hold up thy Hand, and ſo to the reſt of them at the Bar. You of the Jury, Look upon the Priſoners, and hearken to their Cauſe; you ſhall underſtand that they ſtand Indicted in <hi>London</hi> by the Names of <hi>Tho. Tonge,</hi> late of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo as in the Indictment aforementioned, who together with <hi>James Hind,</hi> who ſtands Convicted by his own Confeſſion, and the reſt alſo aforementioned: and ſo reads the Indictment again.</p>
                  <p>Upon which Indictment they have been Arraigned, &amp; thereunto have ſeverally plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Not guilty; &amp; for their Trial have put themſelves upon God &amp; the Countrey, which Countrey you are. Your Charge is to enquire whether they be guilty of the High-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in manner and form as they ſtand Indicted, or not guilty. If you find that they or any of them are guilty, you ſhall enquire what Goods &amp; Chattels, Lands and Tenements, they or any of them had at the time of committing the ſaid Treaſon, or at any time ſithence: If you find that they are not guilty, you ſhall enquire whether they or any of them did flee for it; if you find that they fled for it, you ſhall enquire of their Goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if you had found them guilty. If you find that they are not guilty, nor that they did flee; ſay ſo, and no more, and hear your Evidence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Edw. Turner.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>MAy it pleaſe your Lordſhips, and you Gentlemen that are Sworn of this Jury, the Five Priſoners at the Bar, by the names of <hi>T. Tonge, G. Phillips, F. Stubbs, J. Sallers,</hi> and <hi>N. Gibbs,</hi> do ſtand Indicted for that they as falſe Traytors, together with ſeveral other perſons mentioned in the Indictment, the 31. of <hi>October</hi> laſt, did, in the Pariſh of St. <hi>Michaels</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Cornhil, London,</hi> aſſemble and meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, conſult, contrive and deſign to levy War againſt the King, to ſubvert and change the Government as it is now eſtabliſhed, to Depoſe and Kill the King; and in order to effect this, they did likewiſe then and there agree, and deſign to ſeize and take in their hands, the Kings Royal Palace called <hi>Whitehall,</hi> where the King reſides. For this they have been Indicted, Arraigned, and all theſe five have ſeverally pleaded Not guilty: if we prove them guilty, you muſt find them ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96473:7"/>
                  <speaker>Serjeant <hi>Maynard.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>GEntlemen of the Jury, you have heard the Indictment read, you have heard the ſubſtance of it opened; it is in ſhort words, but of as high conſequence as any thing can be; I ſhall open the Particulars of that Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that we conceive will be made good by the Oaths of Witneſſes to be produced to you. You ſee here what the Indictment is, I ſhall inſiſt upon theſe particulars, which I ſhall open and make good to you; firſt, what was their Deſign; next, what was their means of accompliſhment; what encouragements they uſed one to another, and what colours they put upon this wicked action. For the firſt, Gentlemen, I ſhall begin at the higheſt, higher no man can go in this world; that is, to deſign and compaſs, to contrive to put the King himſelf to Death, to ſeize his Perſon; ſome of them called it Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; you know the Engliſh of that, a King Secured. We will go further, for we ſhall prove to you the perſon that with his own wicked Hand undertook the Slaughter and Murder of the King; he did contrive how he might do it, ſometimes when the King was performing an office of Piety to viſit his Mother; other times, when he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create himſelf by Hunting; higher than this they could not go, and this they coloured over with Religion; this merciful King that had pardoned his People beyond their own deſires, and contended to do it, this King they would Murder. Had there been no more, it had been exceeding hainous; but they went farther, their malice reſted not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Perſon, but the Family, the Noble and Excellent Duke of <hi>York</hi> is deſigned to be ſecured likewiſe, and uſed like his Brother: not they only, they went further, the whole Nobility was in deſign; not (Gentlemen) that every one of theſe before you uſed theſe Expreſſions, but they and their Complices, ſome one and ſome another Expreſſion, but all joyned in this, to deſtroy the King and his Family root and branch, that was their expreſſion: King, his Family, Nobility, nay, go down to the Gentry, and it ceaſed not there, they go to the Clergy, as one of the Priſoners at the Bar (as you will hear) did expreſs himſelf, I think it was <hi>Stubbs,</hi> that there ſhould be never a Lawn-ſleeve, never a Circingler ſhould have a hole to hide his head in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I never opened my mouth to that purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serj. <hi>Maynard.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>That will be left to proof: I undertake not of my ſelf to prove this, but to open it let the Witneſſes ſpeak. In diſcourſe ſome went farther than that; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever would not joyn with them in their Deſign (it was one <hi>Strange</hi>) was an Enemy; and thereupon one <hi>Cole,</hi> who is gone, deſerted them; though he was contented to have the King Murdered, the Nation ruined, yet would not agree in that Principle. To ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh this, we ſhall prove to you they did Treat of levying a War, that among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves it was given out that Arms were provided, ſome delivered, and their Deſigns to raiſe Money, ſeizing all the Treaſury at <hi>Whitehall, Worceſter-houſe,</hi> and the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> to ſeize the perſon of the Noble Duke of <hi>Albemarle,</hi> and all about him, and Quarter to be given to none, that was their expreſſions. They did give out among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (for a while there was ſome difference among theſe Foxes, whoſe Tails were tyed together, and had fire in them) and <hi>Tonge</hi> told them (as we ſhall prove) that all parties were now agreed and would joyn: they had framed Declarations to juſtifie their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; framed Papers to raiſe a Mutiny among the Mariners, and encouraged them to joyn with them, this will be proved: for their means, <hi>Phillips</hi> at the Bar undertakes to procure the Word that the Guard in the City had, ſo to betray them. There was a Deſign made for ſeizing the <hi>Tower;</hi> ſeveral men appointed for that purpoſe, they and their Complices were to come there with Papers in their hands as if they were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, and had Accompts to make up; theſe were to go up to thoſe that ſat there to finiſh Accompts. To encourage themſelves, they gave out, that they had dealt with the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and ſecured that Caſtle; if this be proved to you, there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing higher. There was this one pretence, it was given out, (and perchance the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the City are come to your ears) that they had deſigned a Day for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Miſchief; ſeveral days were appointed, one on the Lord Mayors day, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on <hi>Alhallows</hi> Eve. They gave out by a feigned Letter, that there would be a Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre by the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> this was to raiſe a fear and diſcontent among the Nation, to induce them to joyn when this Deſign ſhould be attempted. Gentlemen of the Jury, had they gone on in this wicked purpoſe, having poſſeſſed the people with theſe fears, who could have told how to behave himſelf? And it ſeems ſtrange and wonderful, eſpecially looking upon the perſons, men of little conſideration, deſpicable men, and who live under the Mercies of ſo good a Soveraign, that they ſhould take ſuch a Deſign in their hearts, and undertake the performance. Though the Spear hath not entred into the Sides of our Soveraign, yet it muſt needs Crown his Head with abundance of Thorns, that ſuch people ſhould be deſperately wicked. But we ſhall call
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96473:7"/> our Witneſſes; and when you have heard this proved, we cannot be ſo vncharitable to think you ſhall need any further aggravation, or doubt of your giving a Verdict againſt ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Jeoffry Palmer.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>THeſe few Priſoners at the Bar were not all in this Contrivance, though we have not all their Names; but in the Evidence you will hear, there was a Council of Forty, and then of Six, but none diſcovered. Theſe Six a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ted and infuſed into theſe and divers others what they intended, and then broke up, and gave out all was ready, and would be done on ſuch a day. We ſhall not trouble the Jury with giving Evidence particularly againſt theſe men; they are joyned and knit together in one Cauſe. But hear the Evidence.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Hill, Edward Riggs,</hi> and one <hi>Bradley</hi> were Sworn.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> Speak your knowledge in this buſineſs to my Lords and the Jury.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Hill.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhips, about the middle of <hi>October</hi> laſt, I met <hi>John Baker,</hi> one that is now Indicted, he was a Captain formerly called; I met him in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide;</hi> he meeting me (after a Salutation) invites me to drink with him. I went into a houſe with him. When I was with him, he began to ask me what News there was in the Countrey. I told him I had little to inform him. He told me, if I would ſtay a while, he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell me ſome. I asked him of what nature? ſays he, Not long ago the King went a Hunting, ſent ſome Stags to Sir <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> now the Lord Mayor, and went but with a ſmall Guard, and I could have been one of the Twenty that would have ſlain that Outlandiſh Dog. Then ſaid I, Mr. <hi>Baker,</hi> that's nothing to me; but what other News have you? Saies he, I know thou art right, and I know your Father; there is ſomething on foot in the City, and if you will meet to morrow, I will bring ſome perſons to you, that will give you information. Sir, ſaid I, underſtanding it of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence, and willing to get it out, I will meet you: and we agreed to meet the next morning; that Morning Three perſons came early to my quarters, <hi>Hill</hi> the Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawer, Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> and this Mr. <hi>Riggs;</hi> he appointed them to meet him there, but fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, they being ſtrangers, ſaid nothing to me then, and ſo I departed and left them a drinking; the morrow after he himſelf came to my Lodgings, fetches me out of my bed, and tells me he had appointed ſome perſons on the <hi>Exchange</hi> to give me an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. I went with him thither; and there we met with ſome perſons that were his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and from thence we went to the Ship in <hi>Leadenhal-ſtreet;</hi> and among us was <hi>Hind,</hi> that confeſſed himſelf guilty; and there the buſineſs was fully diſcourſed of what their intention was, that all intereſts were agreed; <hi>Fifth Monarchy-men, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Independents,</hi> and <hi>Fighting-Quakers;</hi> and the Congregational Churches were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, and were reſolved to endeavour their deliverance from Adverſaries at <hi>Whitehal.</hi> Many paſſages more. On the Morrow after we met again, and there met with us <hi>Hind,</hi> and <hi>Brown,</hi> and <hi>Baker;</hi> there we were acquainted of their Magazine and Arms provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and about their Correſpondence in the ſeveral Counties; that they were ſure of <hi>Windſor-Caſtle;</hi> that the head-Gunner and Sergeant there were privy; we had informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning this <hi>Tonge,</hi> as an active perſon in this deſign. I ſtudied to know this <hi>Tonge,</hi> and I was brought to him at his houſe; and there I met one <hi>Ward, Stubbs</hi> and <hi>Hind,</hi> and ſome others, and there we had diſcourſe concerning the buſineſs. <hi>Tonge</hi> told us ſomething of the buſineſs of <hi>Windſor-Caſtle,</hi> and propoſed ſomething in reference to the taking of the <hi>Tower,</hi> what Arms and Men they had for this Deſign; we met many times at the <hi>Ship;</hi> that <hi>Gibbs</hi> we met at <hi>Bridewel-Dock,</hi> and there was <hi>Stubbs</hi> and one <hi>Bearley</hi> with me; there we waited for a Brother of this <hi>Gibbs's</hi> to give us intelligence when the day of the Inſurrection would be: we waited not long, but in came his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and two perſons more, one <hi>Thomas</hi> a Bridler or Bit-maker in <hi>Shooe-lane,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon in a handſome Garb came along with him; his Brother was ſomewhat ſhy (becauſe I was a ſtranger) to ſpeak any thing, but calls for this <hi>Gibbs</hi> and <hi>Stubbs,</hi> and had ſome private diſcourſe with them, and away departed; after they were gone, we deſired to know the Intelligence: they told us, that the Council of Six was broken up, all buſineſs was ſetled, <hi>Ludlow</hi> was Commander in Chief, and <hi>Al-hallows</hi> Eve was the time, that Horſe and Arms were provided. For <hi>Phillips,</hi> that day that the Meetings were intercepted, that the Trained-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ands did ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e them, that day this Gentleman and I (pointing to <hi>Riggs</hi>) came to the Main-guard at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> where Sergeant <hi>Phillips</hi> was with a Buff-Coat, and a Halb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt, and this Gentleman (meaning <hi>Riggs</hi>) ſaluted him and thanked him for his ſervice in ſending down notice to the Meeting to be gone, for he was coming down with the Trained-bande to ſurprize them; he asked him what was the occaſion of the buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e: ſays he, they ſay —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96473:8"/>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Robert Foſter.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Who is that he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>That <hi>Phillips</hi> ſaid, they ſay they were up in the <hi>Wiſt;</hi> and if they were not, I would they were, and here too, for a few would do the work. Upon the Monday after, we met him near the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and ſo likewiſe <hi>Riggs</hi> thanked him for his ſervice, and then he <hi>(Phillips)</hi> promiſed his further ſervice when the time of the Inſurrection would be.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Sallers,</hi> I was by agreement to have Thirty Arms delivered me, and I was very preſſing to have the Arms out of the Magazine. <hi>Sallers</hi> met with this Gentleman <hi>(Riggs)</hi> and he urging <hi>Sallers</hi> about the Arms, <hi>Sallers</hi> told him that they were all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out the night before, about five or ſix hundred, and that forty of their friends went away without Arms; but that within two or three days there would be more laid in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Heneage Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> I will ask you one queſtion (with my Lords favour) as you have given a general account, I will keep you to one particular perſon, <hi>Tonge:</hi> Did <hi>Tonge</hi> in any diſcourſe with you, tell you of one <hi>Strange</hi> that was gone into the Country?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>One night he told us he had ſpoke with <hi>Strange;</hi> that he was gone into the Countrey, and would come back the morrow, and then we ſhould have more intelligence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Heneage Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What concerning the <hi>Tower</hi> and <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>He talked of the good ſervice that he had done in being at <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle, with the Serjeant and Gunner, for the ſecuring of that Caſtle; that near five hundred of their friends were in and about <hi>Windſor,</hi> ready to aſſiſt for ſurprizing that Caſtle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who told you this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tonge</hi> told me himſelf, that he was inſtrumental in it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Finch.</speaker>
                  <p>Did he tell you any thing of the <hi>Tower?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Only he ſaid, it was fit ſome care ſhould be taken to ſurprize the <hi>Tower</hi> at the time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Finch.</speaker>
                  <p>Any thing of <hi>Alhallows</hi>-Eve?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>He did not fix the very inſtant time, but ſaid, he looked for intelligence from <hi>Strange.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Jeoffry Palmer.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What day of the Month was that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot remember the very day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serjeant <hi>Maynard.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What did he ſay concerning Declarations?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>The Declaration was ready, <hi>Stubbs</hi> acquainted us, againſt Popery and Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, for Liberty of Conſcience, and a Free Common-wealth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Finch.</speaker>
                  <p>Any thing of the Popiſh Maſſacre?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I had this Paper of them, a Copy of a Letter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>R. Foſter.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>How many Copies of that Letter were to be diſperſed in the City?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>About five thouſand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Jeoffry Palmer.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Theſe things were to be diſperſed to poſſeſs the people, that the Papiſts about that time would Maſſacre the Proteſtants, that ſo they might draw all againſt that Party to joyn with them; a brave colour, when in truth there was no ſuch thing, but only to carry on their deſign of killing the King, and altering the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>The Letter was read by the Clerk, and follows, <hi>in his verbis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t of the reſpect which I bear to you in particular, and to the Proteſtant Party in general, I give you notice of this paſſage: About a fortnight ſince, a woman, which you muſt be ignorant where, who had it from a Correſpondent of the Papiſts, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make uſe of their Army (which all the World ſees they have provided) againſt <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallows</hi> Eve next; It was thought good therefore, in as prudent a way as may be, to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to our friends in remote parts, that they may do what Piety to God, Loyalty to their Prince, Love to their Country, and ſelf-preſervation ſhould direct them. Sir, I call the Eternal God to witneſs, that this is not to trepan, to put a trick upon you, but a ſober truth; and alſo commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to a Juſtice of the Peace, and by him to the Privy-Council; and what the iſſue of it is I have not heard; I hope you will inquire and tell us.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>From <hi>Yexford</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> 
                              <date>Octob. <hi>31. 1662.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serj. <hi>Keeling.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Do you (Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>) remember any diſcourſe of the way of taking <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall?</hi> Name who were there, and who ſpoke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>There was <hi>Hind,</hi> and one Captain <hi>Browne</hi> a Shoe-maker in the <hi>Strand,</hi> and ſome other perſons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Was <hi>Stubbs</hi> there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Not at this diſcourſe; but we talked of taking <hi>Whitehall</hi> at <hi>Stubbs</hi>'s houſe, when a Sea-Captain was there that was to go to <hi>Saranam,</hi> and <hi>Stubbs</hi> invited him to ſtay at home to aſſiſt them; who was to come down with a Party by <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96473:8"/> the Party to come up by the Cock-pit, and to kill my Lord Duke of <hi>Albemarle,</hi> and to ſlay Sir <hi>Richard Brown</hi> in the City, and the Party in the City to keep a Drum bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Tonge</hi> ſaid, That their main care muſt be to keep down Sir <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> and the Trained-bands, or elſe they ſhould never be able to ſtand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What concerning the Privy-Garden way?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>They diſcourſed concerning the getting down the Door and the Wall, and ſo get the ſooner to <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What was <hi>Stubbs</hi>'s opinion at that Communication?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>His was at <hi>Black-fryers,</hi> the laſt Tueſday night before they were taken, this <hi>Stubbs, Thomas,</hi> and <hi>Gibbs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Which <hi>Gibbs?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>This black <hi>Gibbs</hi> at the Bar; they diſcourſed that they would be ſure to make an end of Kings, Princes and Dukes, that they might have a Free State, and be troubled no more with any ſuch kind of perſons, neither Lawn-ſleeves, nor Circinglers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you remember that <hi>Stubbs</hi> propoſed any other way to <hi>Whitehall?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maynard.</speaker>
                  <p>Did they ſay what Number was provided, ten, or twenty thouſand?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Stubbs</hi> aſſured as there was a great Party in <hi>Eaſt-Smithfield,</hi> right for the work, and had their Arms.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What Imployment had <hi>Sallers</hi> about delivering the Arms?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſaid, the Arms were delivered out at <hi>Crutched-fryers,</hi> about ſix hundred, and that Forty of their Friends went away laſt night for lack of Arms; that within two or three days there would be more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Did he name a Magazine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, the Magazine in <hi>Crutched-fryers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you know any thing touching the diſcovery of the Word, and by whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Sir; but I underſtood that <hi>Tonge</hi> was aſſured by <hi>Philips,</hi> that <hi>Phillips</hi> would get him the Word that very night that they intended the Inſurrection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What was propounded, if they had taken the King, what would they do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſhould have the ſame Quarter as <hi>Ludlow</hi> was to have.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who ſaid that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Stubs, Gibbs,</hi> and <hi>Tonge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>That's three of the Priſoners at the Bar. Lord have mercy upon us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Were you not acquainted of a Council of Six?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, they named ſome at a venture, but they believed ſome of them were of the Six. That they met not twice in a place, ſometimes here, and ſometimes in another place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Who did they name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Colonel <hi>Danvers, Phillips, Nye</hi> the Miniſter, <hi>Lockyer,</hi> and one <hi>Cole</hi> of <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> that theſe Five were part of the Six.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What diſcourſe touching the diſtance of place where they engaged any?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Forty miles about the Town.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Did <hi>Tonge</hi> tell you that <hi>Strange</hi> had lodg'd any Horſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſaid, he had taken out the Horſe that were provided for a time, but <hi>Gibbs</hi> and <hi>Stubs</hi> at <hi>Black-fryers</hi> aſſured us of the Horſe coming into the Town the night before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Did <hi>Tonge</hi> tell you of any Back, Breaſts, Blunderbuſſes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Not he, Sir, it was talked of that night at the <hi>Black-fryers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What did you hear concerning ſending into <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> to ſpread Rumours there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>That they had four hundred of their Friends there that they were ſure of, and ſeveral Caſes of Piſtols ſent down by the Carrier.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who ſaid that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not what particular perſon, but at that Meeting and in that company.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Who was preſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gibbs</hi> and <hi>Stubbs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>None of the reſt? Was <hi>Tonge</hi> or <hi>Phillips</hi> there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you hear of any other Countrey, either <hi>Kent,</hi> or <hi>Worceſterſhire,</hi> or <hi>Derby,</hi> or <hi>Leiceſterſhire?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tonge</hi> informed us of the faithfulneſs of Colonel <hi>Kendrick</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> to bring him ſome Arms.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>If the Priſoners will ask him any Queſtions, they may.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>Friends, all that here are preſent, I did ever abhor ſuch an action: Ask him whether he did hear me ſpeak thoſe words, that I would ſay, That there was Arms delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out, and that forty went away lacking, and in one or two days there wou'd be more; which words I never did ſpeak in my life, or any ſuch thing; only what I heard from <hi>Wapſhot,</hi> as <hi>Wapſhot</hi> declared to my Lord Mayor he told me, to whom I appeal. It's true, meeting with that <hi>Wapſhot,</hi> ſays he, We hear there will be a Riſing, and there are ſome Arms delivered out; ſaid I, I would adviſe you to have a care of ſuch a buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96473:9"/>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Orl. Bridgman.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I would not interrupt you, you will be admitted to make your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence afterwards; but if you will, ask him any Queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I ſhall come to that. <hi>Wapſhot</hi> told me the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e were Arms delivered, but further told me, he knew not of the certainty of theſe things; that at night he ſhould go to a houſe where he ſhould know. I bid him have a care. At night as I was paſſing along I met <hi>Riggs</hi> at <hi>Stubbs</hi> door, he asked me what news at <hi>London?</hi> I ſaid, I was told there would be a Riſing, and that Arms were delivered: Is there? ſays he; ſaid I, I do not believe it, but I ſhall know certainly to morrow. I did call the next morning, and asked, Is the ſtory true? No, ſays he, I was there, and there was no Arms: that was all that I know of the buſineſs. Friend, did I tell you any ſuch thing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell him, and upon what occaſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Upon occaſion of <hi>Riggs</hi> asking him for thirty Arms for me, (this upon the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change) Sallers</hi> took him a little aſide, and told him, They were all delivered out; that forty went away lacking that more would be there within two or three days.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>That which I ſaid to <hi>Riggs,</hi> was the Meſſage I received from <hi>Wapſhot;</hi> but that I inquired, and there was no Arms there; ſo that it was but a fallacy; For I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him not to meddle with any ſuch thing. Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> never ſaw my face, till I was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended upon the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and brought before Sir <hi>Rich. Brown.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſaw him upon the <hi>Exchange</hi> with this man <hi>(Riggs.)</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Did he ſay that any Arms were delivered before, and what number?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>About five or ſix hundred.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>He never heard me ſpeak a word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>How long before he was apprehended?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Never but that time with <hi>Riggs</hi> upon the <hi>Exchange,</hi> about nine days before his apprehenſion; and he confeſſed upon his examination, That he did ſee me with <hi>Riggs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you, or any other the Priſoners, any Queſtions more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>I have more: Whether he will poſitively affirm that he ſpake with me upon the <hi>Exchange?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Sir, you anſwered the queſtion to <hi>Riggs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>You heard the anſwer?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>May be at the ſecond hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you hear the priſoner anſwer it, or had you it at the ſecond hand?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>I heard it from <hi>Sallers</hi> himſelf, anſwering <hi>Riggs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you hear me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, to Mr. <hi>Riggs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Hen. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>He ſwears it, and you wonder at it, and ſo we do all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>Who was there then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>It was upon the <hi>Exchange</hi> when almoſt full.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>What day of the month?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot remember the day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>I do declare before this Honourable Bench, Gentlemen of the Jury, and this great Auditory, That I never ſaw this mans face till I was apprehended: That which I told Mr. <hi>Riggs,</hi> was, what I heard <hi>Wapſhot</hi> ſay. I never till then ſaw this mans face, nor exchanged one word with him; whereas he ſaies, he heard me, I do not believe Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> ſaw him near me, when I gave him the anſwer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Seeing he doth invalidate my Teſtimony, Mr. Adjutant <hi>Carent</hi> took him upon the <hi>Exchange,</hi> I ſhewed him the perſon; and therefore, certainly I muſt ſee him before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>It was not he, but the other in the white cloaths, that came and took me, that knew me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Will any of the reſt ask him any queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>Here is that that I am accuſed of, That I delivered Arms, which is altogether falſe; My Lord Mayor can bear me witneſs, <hi>Wapſhot</hi> confeſſed he told me ſuch a thing; I was always ſerviceable to his Majeſty upon all occaſions, and all times: my Neighbours can witneſs my civil Converſation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you any thing more to ask him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>I would fain know, whether the Bench and Jury are ſatisfied with this Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>That you will hear anon: What elſe will you ask him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>What he accuſes me, you have all heard: I do in the preſence of God, and this Honourable Bench, and the Jury, deny it; for it is very falſe, and believe none will verifie the ſame upon Oath.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you any queſtions?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>We all ſtand in the preſence of God; and I am very conſcientious of what I ſay and do, I muſt give account of all things before the Lord. This Gentleman, Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> has aſſerted concerning me, That I ſhould deliver divers Caſes of Piſtols, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the delivery of them: if Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> who ſtands likewiſe in the preſence of God, can produce any man to prove, that I delivered to any man any Piſtols, or that any were ſo delivered by my order, or that I conveyed or ſent them a way into the Countrey; do this in the light of the Lord and his own conſcience, I expect no mercy. But I would have him ſpeak no more of me, but what the knows of me, or by me; whether he knows
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96473:9"/> I ever received any Piſtols, or delivered any at any time, for ſuch an end as he is pleaſed to ſpeak; which my Soul abhors, and God can witneſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>This Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> was the man that mentioned this, and that he had four Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Arms himſelf, and had two hundred pound in order to it. I was never any Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor contrived any thing, but am as innocent as the Child unborn; but being by an accident at <hi>Tonges</hi> houſe, a Strong water-man; ask the other Witneſſes whether he ſpeaks truth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>O. Bridgman.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I would put you in a right way, you ſhall be all heard at large, when you make your defence: But will you ask him any queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I propounded one, I deſire an anſwer; Whether I received or delivered any Piſtols to ſuch a uſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>I did not ſay he did; but at that Meeting at <hi>Black-fryers</hi> it was diſcourſed among them, that ſeveral Arms were ſent to <hi>Dorſetſhire</hi> to ſeveral friends there, and he was there then; I believe he cannot deny it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>There was Arms ſpoken of, but that man (Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>) ſpoke of them, and upon this conſideration, that there were Arms delivered to every Hall, Ammunition and Powder: <hi>Riggs</hi> knows he ſpoke it at that time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, that was ſpoken after the queſtion was put, What was the occaſion of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Powder and Ammunition to the Halls? Theſe Arms were ſpoken of, in reference to the deſign, I do acknowledge. I told him I had ſome Arms my ſelf, and ſaid, I had Two hundred pound for carrying it on: and I know the grounds of my ſpeaking, and ſo do ſome of this Honourable Bench.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hill</hi> adviſed, that they fall upon Sir <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> as an enemy to all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>This <hi>Hill</hi> ſays, that I ſhould ſay theſe things: there was more there, and had ears as well as he, let them ſpeak.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>There was <hi>Riggs, Stubbs,</hi> my ſelf, and I know not the other Names.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>This <hi>Hill</hi> and Mr. <hi>Riggs,</hi> whoſe face I never ſaw, came to my Neighbours houſe, where I was alone, found me plotting with no man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>We were brought into his company by one <hi>Beazley</hi> he had been at <hi>Tower-hill</hi> about two or three a clock, to give ſome intelligence to ſome perſons there, about the deſign. <hi>Riggs</hi> and I took a Coach and went after him, and <hi>Stubbs</hi> told us we might meet him at a Bakers houſe near the <hi>Tower.</hi> We found <hi>Beazley,</hi> and he ſaid he could not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie any thing to us, but would carry us to <hi>Black-fryers,</hi> to one <hi>Gibbs;</hi> and there he brought us to this very man, firſt enquiring at a houſe for him. <hi>Beazley</hi> was told, he was at a Tavern at <hi>Bridewel-ſtairs:</hi> We went there and found him; he told us, he could tell us little himſelf, till his Brother came; and accordingly he preſently after came, that was the occaſion that I came into his company.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſays that I ſpoke of Piſtols delivered, and a number, but how many he knows not; and that I ſhould talk of the death of the King, which is as falſe as God is true. Again, I knew not of his coming, never appointed him, never was privy to any ſuch Plot; I abhor it in my Soul, I never engaged in any ſuch deſign with any man at any time</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>You do your ſelf much wrong, and take away that time, which you may happily ſpend better.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I deſire to know of Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> who was preſent at that Meeting, that I ſhould ſay, the King ſhould have ſuch quarter as <hi>Ludlow.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>It was ſpoken at the Meeting at <hi>Black-fryers,</hi> after his Brother and the other perſons were gone: it was there ſpoken, that the Council was broke up, and all ready; <hi>Alhallows</hi>-Eve the time, and then the ſame quarter to be given as <hi>Ludlow</hi> ſhould have if taken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>You do not anſwer the Queſtion: who was there beſides your ſelf?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>There was <hi>Riggs,</hi> and that <hi>Gibbs</hi> there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>You have onely his Evidence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>Who was in company when I talked of Three hundred men at <hi>Windſor?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>It was at your own houſe; and there was <hi>Ward, Stubbs, Riggs, Hind,</hi> and my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phillips.</speaker>
                  <p>Whether did he ever ſee my face at any Meeting?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>I never ſaw you before that time in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phillips.</speaker>
                  <p>Upon what account did I ſpeak to <hi>Riggs</hi> then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hill.</speaker>
                  <p>When you came off the <hi>Exchange,</hi> you told him you could not ſtay, your Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was coming, <hi>Riggs</hi> thanked you for your favour in ſending word to the Meeting to be gone, to a certain Quaker.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96473:10"/>
                  <speaker>Phillips.</speaker>
                  <p>I never ſent to any Quaker to that purpoſe. I did not ſee this man upon the Sabbath-day; but <hi>Riggs</hi> came down to me, and thought I had ſent notice to <hi>Anchor-Alley,</hi> but I did not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>He affirmed that there was ſeveral Meetings of Forty, and then of Six: ask Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> whether I was in either of thoſe numbers at any time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>He did not charge you with any ſuch thing of being in that number: he asks a queſtion about things not laid to his charge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Let Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> ſpeak.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edward Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>About three weeks ſince, I came acquainted with Mr. <hi>Tonge,</hi> upon this occaſion; Captain <hi>Baker</hi> did ſay, that he was a man of Intelligence, but Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> did not care for him; and told me that I might be acquainted with him: a while after I came acquainted with him accidentally, when I came to his Houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Whoſe Houſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tongs</hi> houſe; Mr. <hi>Stubbs</hi> was there; he ſaid, that he had been at <hi>Windſor,</hi> ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the Gunner and Sergeant, and that they promiſed it ſhould be ready upon ſome certain notice given: that night he had received a Letter of ſome buſineſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a ſuit at Law, he ſaid, in which there was a myſtical meaning, which he did not tell me of; but this he ſaid, That he had made ſure of <hi>Windſor,</hi> by the Gunner and Sergeants promiſes. This is that I know of him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Is this all of <hi>Tonge?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>This likewiſe he has told me, that he had ſometimes met with a certain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, he did not ſay Thirty or Forty, but a pretty many there was: he named Mr. <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> Captain <hi>Elton,</hi> Captain <hi>Leigh,</hi> that they had often me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, but could not well agree; but at laſt Mr. <hi>Strange</hi> did meet with them, give them one Meeting; they could not agree neither: they went away, and ſaid theſe words, to the beſt of my remembrance, Mr. <hi>Strange</hi> did refuſe to joyn with them, but when God bids him go, he would go; whether this day, or next week, or next year, matters not; but when God bids him go, he would go. Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> was ſomewhat troubled to hear it; but ſays Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> if you will go, give me but notice, if I cannot go ſo faſt as you ride, I will hold by your Horſe-tail: A little while after he told me, they had not met again; that Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> becauſe they could not agree about this buſineſs, was gone beyond Sea; but before he was gone, he did tell me of ſome conſiderations that were drawn, as he judged, about a Government, by Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> and gave me in a Paper ſome certain Propoſitions, three or four, concerning Sea-men; the ſubſtance was this, what great benefits they had by a Common-wealth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who gave you them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tonge,</hi> but it came from Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> as he ſaid; In general, they were to declare againſt the Miſgovernment of Church and State, in particular to Sea-men, what great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages there would be to them; and three or four things propounded in order to them. 1. That no Sea-men ſhould pay cuſtom for any commodity that he did bring under the value of Ten pounds; upwards they muſt: And likewiſe there ſhould be care taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our own Coaſts, and beyond Sea, that where any of our Engliſh Ships ſhould be caſt away, there ſhould be care taken out of the Cuſtomes, that might keep them in their travelling homewards, either from begging or ſtarving; but Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> when they met, as <hi>Tonge</hi> ſaid, would not agree, and therefore went beyond Sea: after he was gone, within a week or fortnight they had another meeting.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>They, which they? name them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>I did not hear him name many, unleſs <hi>Leigh</hi> and Captain <hi>Elton,</hi> I remember no more; and there, he ſaid, they had under conſideration the Government of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; and ſo to declare againſt the miſgovernment of the Church and State; and there was to be a meeting at <hi>London-wall,</hi> in a little time after, and he was there: He afterwards told me, he miſt that meeting, but had intelligence brought him, that that time that he miſſed, thirty or forty, I know not the certain number, had referred it to Six men; they called it, <hi>The Council of Six,</hi> but the names of them, I never heard from him; and indeed, he ſaid he knew them not, by reaſon of his abſence from that meeting: but what I gathered from him, was this, That he judged Captain <hi>Elton</hi> was one of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>He told you, there was a Council of Six?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Hen. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>To make things ſhort; were you ever at any meeting where there was a diſcourſe touching ſurprizing the King, altering the Govertment? and who was there, upon your Oath?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>That Friday immediately before we were taken, I think <hi>Octber</hi> 24. there was ſome diſcourſe, in general, concerning <hi>Whitehall;</hi> what might be done, as to the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of that, and likewiſe concerning the <hi>Tower.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Who was preſent that Friday?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>My ſelf, <hi>Hill, Tonge, Stubbs, Ward, Hind,</hi> and <hi>John Baker;</hi> and then to the beſt of my knowledge, there was this diſcourſe in general. Concerning the taking of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96473:10"/> 
                     <hi>Tower,</hi> there was ſome Propoſitions on all hands concerning the taking of that; Mr. <hi>Hind,</hi> he only mentioned, but did ſay he would undertake it, the righting of Gunners Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts. Mr. <hi>Tonge,</hi> he ſaid, that the way that he thought convenient, might be this: When Sir <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> now Lord Mayor, did late in the evening go into the <hi>Tower,</hi> there ſhould be a party following his Coach; and ſo might do it. And <hi>John Baker</hi> at that preſent inſtant of time did ſay, That it was neceſſary the King ſhould be ſurprized; and likewiſe ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> then, That there ſhould be no quarter, he would give nor take none.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Who was preſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> my ſelf, <hi>Bradly, Hind,</hi> Captain <hi>Brown,</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> and another <hi>Hill,</hi> the Drawer I think.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Was not <hi>Tonge</hi> and <hi>Stubbs</hi> there then at that time?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, they were there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Hen. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I ask you this: I do not deſire large ſtories, but firm and cloſe anſwers; Were you preſent at any meeting, when the ſecuring of the King, <hi>Tower,</hi> or <hi>Whitehall,</hi> was diſcourſed of, or no?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, that Friday <hi>Octob.</hi> 24. immediately before we were taken, there was this diſcourſe. <hi>Tonge</hi> did propound ſuch a way for ſurprizing the <hi>Tower,</hi> by following Sir <hi>John Robinſons</hi> Coach in at night: and <hi>Baker</hi> did ſay, That it was neceſſary to undertake the ſecuring of the Kings perſon, and aſſaulting of <hi>Whitehall;</hi> and that if there were Five hundred horſe and foot, they would undertake it, by going into the Privy Garden, and Back-ſtairs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Were you preſent when <hi>Stubbs</hi> did adviſe the aſſaulting of <hi>Whitehall,</hi> by the Privy Garden?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>No; but <hi>Baker</hi> did ſay he would undertake it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Who was preſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hill, Bradly, Stubbs,</hi> and <hi>Hind</hi> was there: but that <hi>Stubbs</hi> undertook it I cannot ſay, but he was there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Hen. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Did <hi>Tonge</hi> ever tell you any thing of <hi>Phillips,</hi> or that he had hopes of the Word?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>I came acquainted with <hi>Phillips,</hi> preſently after I was acquainted with Mr. <hi>Tonge. Phillips</hi> once met me, and I carried him to <hi>Tonges,</hi> and then <hi>Phillips</hi> freely ſaid, That there was Three hundred Arms at the <hi>Artillery Garden;</hi> he being one of the Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, knew where they lay, and could tell them how they might come by thoſe Arms; and that for the Word, it was neceſſary to be got; and if in caſe that it ſo fell out that the White Regiment was then out, or he then in office, he would endeavour to procure it: But afterwards meeting him ſeveral times, he declared, he would not meddle any more with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>H. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Were you upon the <hi>Exchange</hi> with <hi>Sallers,</hi> when there was a diſcourſe about delivering out of Arms? and what did <hi>Sallers</hi> ſay?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſaying, That he had Two hundred pound to buy Horſes, and that he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our already, and wanted Swords, and had friends in Town wanted Arms; asked me, if I knew if any were given out. I told him, that one Mr. <hi>Sallers</hi> told me, that he had heard ſome Arms were given, and to be given out that day. Upon the <hi>Exchange,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> and <hi>Bradley,</hi> and I being together, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſaid, I there is the perſon that told me of the Arms; I will go and ask him if there be any ſuch thing. Whether Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> heard the diſcourſe, I cannot tell, but he ſaid, ſays he, I have enquired, and ſome Arms are delivered, and forty went without; but within two or three days there would be more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Hen. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Did <hi>Hill</hi> ſee <hi>Sallers</hi> upon the <hi>Exchange</hi> at that time?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, but whether he heard him, I cannot tell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>R. Foſter.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What induces you to believe he did ſee him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>We were cloſe together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Foſter.</speaker>
                  <p>What about <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>For <hi>Gibbs,</hi> I brought Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> acquainted with Mr. <hi>Stubbs;</hi> and he ſaid he knew one at <hi>Fleet-bridge</hi> that ſells Plums and ſuch things; and if we would go along with him, he would tell us news. <hi>Hill, Stubbs,</hi> and I; that day I was taken, went to <hi>Beazley; Stubbs</hi> asked him what news; ſays he, I hear the buſineſs goes on; but if you will go to one <hi>Gibbs,</hi> meaning him that is fled, he has intelligence. So we went to an Ale-houſe near him, but he was not at home; and we were told, if we ſhould go to <hi>Bridewell,</hi> they ſaid they would ſend for his Brother, meaning him at the Bar, and ſo would have an account. <hi>Gibbs</hi> at the Bar being with us, he told us he knew little himſelf, but when his Brother came, we ſhould hear.. Three quarters of an hour after came <hi>Gibbs</hi> that is gone, <hi>Thomas</hi> and another man. I knew him not, and <hi>Gibbs</hi> called this Brother; <hi>Beazley, Stubbs,</hi> and <hi>Hill,</hi> and I ſet ſtill: when this <hi>Gibbs</hi> came, he ſaid his Brother knew little, hoped we were honeſt men. The news was this, that he heard that <hi>Ludlow</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96473:11"/> was in Town, and that now the Council was broken up.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>What Council?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>The Council of Six was broken up, and that they had ſent Meſſengers into the Countrey, to give notice, and to make their intereſts good abroad: this is that he ſaid there, or as much as I remember.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Finch.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I will ask you in general; Did you ever hear of any diſcourſe at any time of theſe Meetings, touching a Riſting by the Papiſts, and a Maſſacre of the Proteſtants?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>Being upon the <hi>Exchange, Hill, Bradley,</hi> and I, there was a Lieu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nant came to me, and asked me whether I heard of the Maſſacre to be; I ſaid no: ſays he, I can let you ſee a Copy of a Letter to that purpoſe, and gave it me: <hi>Hill</hi> going to the <hi>Ship,</hi> I told him of this, and he was deſirous of having a Copy; and this was the Copy that was this day read in Court.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Jeff. Palmer.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What did you hear concerning the ſurprizing of the King at <hi>Camberwell,</hi> when he came from his Mother? and what did <hi>Phillips</hi> ſay?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Phillips, Tonge, Stubbs,</hi> and my ſelf, being together, they were diſcourſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kings going abroad; and at that <hi>Phillips</hi> ſaid, the King was to come to <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> to ſee the Queen-Mother at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> and hinted that he might be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized. <hi>Tonge</hi> ſaid, it need not; there might be ſuch an opportunity twice every week.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Priſoners, will you ask the Witneſſes any Queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phillips.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you not meet me on a Sabbath-day? you may remember I met you in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> we walked to <hi>Burchin-lane</hi> end: you asked me of a Riſing that ſhould be. I ſaid, What riſing? ſays you, To ſurprize the King, coming from <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> to <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich:</hi> and I came and ſpoke it openly in my Family, as news that I heard. This Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman had me to <hi>Tonges</hi> houſe, and there grew the diſcourſe; <hi>Riggs</hi> told me, <hi>Tonge</hi> could tell further; and <hi>Riggs</hi> told me, that the reaſon why the time for it was not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, was becauſe the Fifth-Monarchy-men and Anabaptiſts were not agreed. <hi>Riggs,</hi> did not I diſclaime this buſineſs, and declared I would have nothing to do with it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>This is certain, that afterwards he did ſay he would not have any thing to do with it, and I did not ſee him a great while after that: Concerning <hi>Bakers</hi> ſurprizing the King, it is true, he did ſay before <hi>Hill</hi> and I, and <hi>Bradſley,</hi> that the King was a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and came through the City; and ſaid, he would have been one of the Fifty that would have ſurprized him, and pulled him out of the Coach.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who ſaid that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baker.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who preſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bradley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> and the other <hi>Hill, Brown,</hi> and others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Finch.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you remember no diſcourſe concerning the coming in at the Privy-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>I have under my hand to the Grand-Jury declared, that <hi>Baker</hi> ſaid he knew the way to the Back-ſtairs through the Privy-Garden, better than any; and <hi>Bradley</hi> did once, and but once, ſay, that he knew it as well as any, and would undertake to do the ſame, in the preſence of <hi>Stubbs, Tonge, Hill,</hi> and the reſt of them that were there that Friday night.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who were the reſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hill,</hi> my ſelf, <hi>Ward, Stubbs, Hind,</hi> and <hi>John Baker,</hi> at <hi>Tongs</hi> houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>John Maynard.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>We do not conceive, that theſe two witneſſes have given Evidence againſt all of them; if any thing ſtick with the Jury, let them ſpeak.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Hear <hi>Bradley;</hi> this witneſs that we call, he was no Conſpirator; but when there was notice of the deſign, he was imployd to find it out, and to give us an account of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Heneage Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr <hi>Bradley,</hi> were you preſent at any debate?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>Whether did <hi>Riggs</hi> hear me ſay, that <hi>Ludlow</hi> was in Town, or that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil was broke up, and the buſineſs went forward?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>This I ſaid, That <hi>Hill, Stubbs,</hi> and <hi>Beazly,</hi> were preſent; and he ſaid, he knew nothing himſelf, but from his Brother; this was the news, that he heard that <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> was in Town, Council broke up, and that there was ſent out Meſſengers to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to prepare for the buſineſs; that it would be on <hi>Alhallows-Eve,</hi> or the latter end of the week, being Saturday the next day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I never ſpake theſe words, and do deſire that the Honourable Bench will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the perſons, then preſent, Whether they will avouch the ſame; whether I ſaid it from my Brother. Theſe words I did not ſpeak; and others being preſent, had ears as well as he.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> told me <hi>Ludlow</hi> was in Town, and told me he would enquire after him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs, I did ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>And that he was like to be taken in <hi>Cheapſide;</hi> he was continually at my ſhop, and would not let me alone, prompting and inducing me to theſe things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> were you at any meeting touching diſcourſe of ſurprizing <hi>Whitehall?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96473:11"/>
                  <speaker>Bradley.</speaker>
                  <p>I was on Friday night at <hi>Tonges</hi> houſe a Strong-water-man on <hi>Tower-Ditch,</hi> where there was theſe two Gentleman with me (pointing to Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Riggs,</hi>) and there was Mr. <hi>Stubbs,</hi> and <hi>John Baker,</hi> and another Gentlemen, one <hi>Ward;</hi> and we had ſome diſcourſe about ſurprizing of <hi>Whitehall,</hi> which way it might be done. Some ſaid, that a party might go through the Guard, and ſo ſurprize General <hi>Monks</hi> Guard: Others ſaid, they might come down by <hi>Charing-Croſs;</hi> but <hi>Tonge</hi> ſaid, there was no coming down by <hi>Charing-Croſs,</hi> becauſe there was two great Guns planted at the bottom, and commanded all that way; but ſaid, the only way he conceived, was to bring a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through <hi>Kings-ſtreet,</hi> and if it were poſſible to get into the <hi>Privy-Garden,</hi> and ſo into the Lodgings that way. This is all that I remember.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serj. <hi>Keeling.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Do you know any thing about the Ship at the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> houſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bradley.</speaker>
                  <p>I went to this Ship ſometimes; and with <hi>Riggs, Hill, Brown, Hind,</hi> and one <hi>Hill</hi> a Cloath-drawer, we had divers diſcourſes concerning the deſign, and the news on foot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>What deſign? expreſs it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bradley.</speaker>
                  <p>To alter the Government, the ſurprizing the King, the Duke, and the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and as many more of the Council they could lay hands on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What about the Guards, ſurprizing <hi>Whitehall?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bradley.</speaker>
                  <p>At another meeting they diſcourſed about bringing forces to <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Who were preſent then? which of the priſoners at the Bar?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bradley.</speaker>
                  <p>None, unleſs <hi>Hind</hi> be there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>At what other meetings were you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bradley.</speaker>
                  <p>I was never at any other, but twice at <hi>Tonges</hi> houſe. The Friday night we had a diſcourſe about taking <hi>Whitehall;</hi> and the day before we were taken, I met this Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> upon the <hi>Exchange;</hi> he asked me to go home and dine with him; we intended to go and ſee a Ship: His Dinner being not ready, we went over to <hi>Tonges</hi> Shop, and had a quartern of Strong-waters, and I took a Pipe of Tobacco. <hi>Riggs</hi> went away, and ſaid he would not ſtay; <hi>Hind</hi> ſtaid with me the whilſt. After we had taken a Pipe of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, he came again, and ſaid he heard the buſineſs was near at hand, and that there would be ſpeedy action. <hi>Hill</hi> was at the ſhop, and after dinner <hi>Riggs</hi> and I, Mr <hi>Hill;</hi> and <hi>Hind,</hi> went all out together to <hi>Stubbs</hi> his houſe. <hi>Riggs</hi> and <hi>Hill</hi> went in, <hi>Hind</hi> and I ſtaid. Standing there a little, ſaid I to <hi>Hind,</hi> What mean theſe Gentlemen to ſtay ſo long? <hi>Riggs</hi> ſaid he ſtaid for a friend; but I will go and meet him: Said I, Will you not go on board a ſhip with Mr. <hi>Hind</hi> and I? ſays <hi>Riggs,</hi> No, I will go to meet my friend. Do you go on board the ſhip, and come to my houſe; If I am not there, pray ſtay a little. We asked Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> if he would go with us, but he went with <hi>Riggs;</hi> and they told me coming back, that <hi>Gibbs</hi> had informed them, the deſign was ready, Council broke up, and Meſſengers ſent to give notice, and <hi>Ludlow</hi> in Town, and to be General.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who told you this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bradley.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Riggs</hi> did, when he returned from <hi>Bridewell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tyler</hi> Sworn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>H. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>M. <hi>Tyler,</hi> do you know <hi>Tonge?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>I know him very well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>H. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Have you ever been in his company, and ſpake of any deſign about ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the King?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>Often.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell what you have heard.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>I have met Mr. <hi>Tonge,</hi> and others, in three or four ſeveral places; at the <hi>Wheat-ſheaf</hi> at <hi>Lions,</hi> once if not twice; at the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> Widow <hi>Jordans</hi> within <hi>Biſhops-gate,</hi> twice at the leaſt; near <hi>Dukes-place</hi> at the <hi>Sheares.</hi> I have heard ſeveral things, and have noted it down, to be ſure to deliver the truth. I have heard them ſpeak about <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and ſecuring of it, and of the two Guns there. <hi>Elton</hi> and he ſaid that they might come with a Party backwards, breaking through a Barbers ſhop in <hi>Kings-ſtreet,</hi> and diſmount the two Guns. But as touching the King, the Duke, and the Noble Duke of <hi>Albemarl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> they propoſed what excellent ſervice it would be to ſecure theſe perſons. He ſaid it was not a thing that would admit of much debate; in as much as he had a friend a Courtier, (I know not his Title) that would give him notice at any time when the King was gone a Hunting, or his progreſs; and that it was eaſie to take it. <hi>Tonge</hi> ſaid he ſerved the <hi>Tower</hi>-Sutler, and was acquainted there; and ſaid, there was no way to ſurprize that but this: either about ten or eleven a clock, I will undertake we may do it with forty perſons, thus, ſays he, ſome to go in dropping, one by one, or two together; and others to be at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ale-houſes neer, to be ready; and they within ſeizing on the Guard by a private ſign, we would ſecure thoſe without; and the Soldiers being of the old Army, will readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comply: And ſaid, there was a perſon that lived nigh him, wears Ropes about him, is a Porter when off the Guard; and believes he can command the whole Company, and would undertake it. For <hi>Windſor</hi>-caſtle, there was an old Gunner that he kept a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence withal, and he ſerves the Sutlers of that Caſtle with Tobacco, I think he named Strong-water; and that the Souldiers were many of them of his acquaintance,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96473:12"/> and that he had received Letters from this Gunner, under ſome ſtrange title, and ſaid it was eaſie, and knew, that at any time, when Word was given, let him go or ſend by ſuch a token, and that place were our own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Who ſaid this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Tonge.</hi> As to the other perſon <hi>Phillips,</hi> I can only ſay this of him; There is one Lieutenant <hi>Chapman,</hi> ſo formerly, now a Priſoner in the <hi>Tower:</hi> This Lieutenant was a Carrier of <hi>Norwich.</hi> I went to his Inn the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet,</hi> and asked for him. I was told he was at Captain <hi>Foſters</hi> houſe in <hi>Leaden-hall-ſtreet,</hi> and there I might find him. I went to Captain <hi>Foſters,</hi> and Captain <hi>Foſters</hi> man told me he was at Supper there with his Maſter: I went up, there was this Lieutenant <hi>Chapman,</hi> and <hi>Phillips;</hi> which was the firſt time I laid eyes on <hi>Phillips:</hi> My buſineſs was to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the Carrier; but I perceived by ſome diſcourſe of Mr. <hi>Phillips,</hi> there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing driving on: but I muſt ſay, that Captain <hi>Foſter</hi> walked about the Room, as if he minded not the diſcourſe; there was <hi>Chapman, Phillips, Elton,</hi> and a man looking a ſquint, I heard <hi>Phillips</hi> call him Muſter-Maſter, but I know not the man; I heard them diſcourſe very promiſcuouſly about ſhips, and ſomething wildly. I tarried while I ſpent my two pence, and came away with Mr. <hi>Chapman,</hi> and asked him what that young Blade was that talked ſo promiſcuouſly? <hi>Chapman</hi> told me he was a Serjeant belonging to the Trained-Bands: Tell me his Name? his Name is <hi>Phillips:</hi> Do you know his Trade or Dwelling? He is a Gilder I think: Then this is the ſame perſon I have heard of at a Coffee-houſe, which was thus: A Perfumer in <hi>Southwark,</hi> he heard of great Rumours about a new Commonwealth; and preſſing this Perfumer how he came to be thus informed; ſays he, there is one <hi>Phillips</hi> that lives in <hi>Abchurch</hi>-lane, this man knows of it: For, ſaies he, he hath ſaid himſelf, that he has gone from Committee to Committee, where Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers met about theſe things, and he named Captain <hi>Foſter</hi> for one that was ingaged in the buſineſs: ſaid I, This is ſtrange. I haſtened back again in the morning to Captain <hi>Foſters:</hi> Sir, ſaid I, Do you know that <hi>Phillips</hi> that was here laſt night? Yes, ſays he What is he? ſaid I; he anſwered, A Serjeant. The thing is this; this man does talk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, That there is a meeting of the old Officers, and that you are engaged. At which, Captain <hi>Foſter</hi> ſeemed to be troubled that he ſhould be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſperſed; anſwered, I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, not one word of this. I do declare an abhorrence thereto, or of any action againſt His Majeſty; and thereupon preſently went to <hi>Phillips,</hi> and charged him with this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; and ſoon after, this Perfumer comes to my houſe, and deſired me to go over to the <hi>Croſs-Keys,</hi> where <hi>Phillips</hi> was. When I came there, ſays <hi>Phillips,</hi> Sir, I ſaw you the laſt night, when we were talking of Ships, I hope you do not mind the report about Captain <hi>Foſter;</hi> for I am troubled ſuch a thing is mentioned: For my part, I knew not that I ſaid ſo; I am ſure, I knew no ſuch thing. This was all as to <hi>Phillips:</hi> But for <hi>Tonge</hi> I muſt needs ſay, in all meetings where I was, the ſeveral places that I formerly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and the <hi>Whalebone</hi> behind the <hi>Exchange,</hi> he ſtill diſcourſed of this buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What was done there concerning the chuſing the Council of Six?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>He was ſpoke to be at the <hi>Shears,</hi> but he ſent a Note ſealed and directed, in which was incloſed either nine or eleven of the Rump-Parliament names of perſons: And, ſays he, for my part I cannot come this day, becauſe the Hamlets are to go out into the Field; it was when Sir <hi>John Robinſon</hi> marched with his Regiment; that I may avoid ſuſpicion, I muſt go with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What were thoſe names?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot tell; but they were nine or eleven of thoſe in the <hi>Tower:</hi> And he promiſed he would get a note of thoſe mens names in the <hi>Tower;</hi> for he was confident of it, that they would ſit as Members, and do good ſervice upon the account of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: And ſaid there were ſome that had a correſpondency with them in the <hi>Tower.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>What correſpondency had they in the Country?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tonge</hi> told me at the <hi>Wheat-ſheaf,</hi> That if a Riſing ſhould be, it were neceſſary that the old Commanders up and down the Country ſhould head them: And therefore, ſays he, What forces can be raiſed, ſhould go under that Conduct; or to that effect: he and <hi>Elkin</hi> did propoſe ſeveral Colonels, I think moſt that are now living, both in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and beyond the Seas.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Can you tell any thing of the rumours abroad, expecting this deſign?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tonge</hi> told me this, That there was one that they called the Lord <hi>Lockhart,</hi> he, ſaid he, was Governour of <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> that he had thirty or forty ſervants about him; that theſe perſons expected a riſing; and that they and himſelf would engage. We heard that Col. <hi>Roſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ter,</hi> not particularly from <hi>Tonge,</hi> but there in company, was expected to be at <hi>Sturbridg</hi>-Fair, to Head Fifteen hundred Horſe to be at <hi>London.</hi> Alſo, he asked me
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96473:12"/> this queſtion at his houſe, Whether I was acquainted with Captain <hi>Leigh,</hi> a man with one arm, a ſtout honeſt fellow, and an active man of his acquaintance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>Speak your knowledge, both of perſons and things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>There was one Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> of <hi>Southampton, Swetnam, Gibbs</hi> a Hat-maker, not he at the Bar, <hi>Tonge, Thomas Elton, Elkin, Pryor,</hi> and one <hi>Cox</hi> a Gardiner, and <hi>Ward</hi> now Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and one <hi>Ward</hi> a <hi>Southwark</hi>-man, and <hi>Dyer</hi> a young Scholar; there was one <hi>Roſe</hi> of <hi>Cheſterfield,</hi> and the Perfumer I ſpoke of, I know not his name, he lives in <hi>Southwark;</hi> and there was a Quaker, I know not his name: the great buſineſs was to unite all intereſts; <hi>Elkin</hi> ſaid, there were ſeveral Meetings in St. <hi>Martins,</hi> and other places.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>If there be any of the ſix in <hi>London,</hi> I believe this Mr. <hi>Tyler</hi> is one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>To clear that I am none of them, I will name thoſe whom I ſaid were the ſix; <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Shoe-lane</hi> the Copper-ſmith, one <hi>Elton</hi> in <hi>White-chappel,</hi> one <hi>Raddon,</hi> Captain <hi>Spurway</hi> of <hi>Tiverton,</hi> a Weſt Country Gentleman, Dr. <hi>Ward</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi> a Miniſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Hen. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Did <hi>Tonge</hi> tell you that the time was appointed when the Riſing ſhould be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>I know nothing of that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maynard.</speaker>
                  <p>What about <hi>Leiceſter?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hill</hi> ſaid he dwelt there, and came from ſome that dwelt there, and others in <hi>Gloceſterſhire;</hi> but there was another perſon with <hi>Stubbs</hi> and <hi>Tonge,</hi> and ſaid there was a report in the Countrey that there would be ſome riſing; and he came to Town to bring his Child to put him Apprentice with his Brother, and would go down again and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the certainty of the news. He was one of <hi>Lamberts</hi> Souldiers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phillips.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Tyler,</hi> did not you come in with the Carrier of <hi>Norwich</hi> to Captain <hi>Foſters?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I did not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phillips.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſure I came accidentally to Captain <hi>Foſters,</hi> and ſaw you there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>Did I tell you, Mr. <hi>Riggs,</hi> that my brother ſaid <hi>Ludlow</hi> was in Town, and there would be a riſing ſhortly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hill, Beaſly, Stubbs,</hi> and I and you, were together; Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> and your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came in: your Brother <hi>Beaſly, Stubbs,</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> were private in diſcourſe: when you came again to us, we asked you what news? you ſaid, before we came you knew not much, but your Brother could tell; but then you ſaid <hi>Ludlow</hi> was in Town, the Council was broke up, and that Meſſengers were ſent to give notice to the Countrey.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny that ere my Brother ſaid ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Maynard.</speaker>
                  <p>Know you any thing of ſurprizing the Kings Council, or <hi>Whitehall,</hi> or any thing of that, of altering the Government?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>As for altering the Govenment, that muſt needs be deſigned; for <hi>Tonge</hi> ſaid it was debated, and thought convenient, as being the deſire of ſeveral in the Country, that the old Parliament ſhould be choſen again; that was to ſay, that ſo many of them that had approved themſelves faithful from firſt to laſt to the Common-wealths intereſt, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the times of Diſſention. Secondly, that none ſhould have power to elect, or be elected, but ſuch alſo as have approved themſelves faithful, as aforeſaid. Thirdly, this Houſe was to be filled up within a Month. Fourthly, that it ſhould continue one year, and no more. Fifthly, that they ſhould not have power in things of an Eccleſiaſtical na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to impoſe any thing upon the Conſciences of the people. Sixthly, that it ſhould be High-Treaſon among them to aſſert the intereſt of a King, houſe of Lords, or ſingle perſon. Seventhly, that they ſhould not appoint any Salary-Officers. Eighthly, that while they keep to this, it ſhould be High-Treaſon to diſturb them. As touching Arms and things of that nature, the truth is, the buſineſs which was very much urged is this; that there ſhould be an uniting of all intereſts together, Quakers, Fifth monarchy men, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts, Independents, Presbyterians, and Levellers; to which purpoſe every one was obliged at the Meeting to ſee what intereſt they could make among the Presbyters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they looked upon them as perſons that had moſt money and ſtrength. I think there was no Presbyterian ſpoken of except one, who is lately ſecured in the <hi>Tower;</hi> he ſaid, that if ſo be Col. <hi>Beanes</hi> was at liberty, he believed he could engage him. There was one man that was there, which was one <hi>Prior,</hi> I ſuppoſe <hi>Tonge</hi> knew him; he ſaid, he had very much acquaintance with the Presbyters, knew many in the Countrey, and that there they did not meet with any difficulties as here; for all intereſts, Quakers, and Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, and the reſt, are all agreed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Hen. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Very well; you ſee <hi>Tonge</hi> was at all theſe Meetings, at the <hi>Wheat-ſheaf</hi> and <hi>Sheares,</hi> and there were the Colonels propoſed. Did you hear of any Orders given out, in any of theſe Conſultations, to make the riſing in the Countrey at the ſame time as in <hi>London?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96473:13"/>
                  <speaker>Tyler.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Gibbs</hi>'s Brother told us, that he kept a Correſpondence in the Countrey, that in <hi>Eſſex</hi> he knew there were divers Horſe ready there; and I my ſelf ſpoke with one who is lately ſecured, who ſaid, there were divers Horſe ready thereabouts. I remember there were ſeveral at the <hi>Half-moon</hi> at <hi>Biſhops-gate;</hi> one <hi>Smith</hi> a <hi>Northamptonſhire</hi> man, and one <hi>Eloſe</hi> of <hi>Cheſterfield,</hi> and <hi>Tonge;</hi> and we heard that at <hi>Mansfield</hi> and <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> there was a riſing intended; and it was aſſured, that the Countrey was very ripe and forward for action. We were informed, that there was 200 Horſe at <hi>Briſtol:</hi> one perſon not yet ſecured, did affirm to us, that one Col. <hi>Templar</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> had two or three thouſand men ready, his name was <hi>Thomas;</hi> that <hi>Templar</hi> was now in Town, if we would we might go and ſpeak with him. Said, I, ſurely he doth but tell you this; ſaith he, his Lieutenant Col. gave me this Information, and aſſures me, that this Colonel had converted his Eſtate into Money, to pay his Souldiers. Upon this, having occaſion to go down into <hi>Eſſex,</hi> I promiſed <hi>Tonge</hi> I would enquire further there; and underſtanding that one <hi>Thornback</hi> a Glover was one of <hi>Templars</hi> men formerly, I went to his houſe, and being not at home, I rode to <hi>Holſted</hi> Fair, and riding there, the man pulled me by the Coat, for he knew me; ſaith he, Mr. <hi>Tyler,</hi> my ſervant ſaid you were at my houſe to ſpeak with me. Yes, ſaid I, I underſtand your name is <hi>Thornback,</hi> that you can give me ſome account concerning Col. <hi>Templar;</hi> we hear in <hi>London,</hi> that he hath two or three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men in readineſs. I pray inform me, ſaith he, I do not believe any ſuch matter I have ſerved him long, and if occaſion were he would be for you. I asked him the news; ſaith he, We all dread a Maſſacre; we underſtand by a Letter from <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> that the Papiſts intend a Maſſacre of all Proteſtants about <hi>Alhallontide,</hi> and that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey was in great fear about it. This <hi>Thomas</hi> the Copperſmith told us another ſtory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome Roman-Catholicks in <hi>Southwark,</hi> that had a purpoſe to riſe and take off all Phanaticks.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>After this the Court directed that <hi>Phillips</hi>'s Examination ſhould be ſhewed him at the Bar, and he acknowledged his hand thereto, and was read as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="deposition">
                           <head>The Examination of <hi>George Phillips</hi> Serjeant and Bringer up to Col. Sir <hi>William Wale</hi>'s Company of Trained-bands in the City of <hi>London,</hi> taken this 29 of <hi>October,</hi> 1662. before me <hi>Richard Brown.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Who ſaith,</hi> THat he knoweth one Parſon <hi>Riggs,</hi> late Chaplain to <hi>Blake,</hi> who is now Clerk to one <hi>Friend,</hi> a Brewer in <hi>Cats-hole,</hi> near the <hi>Iron-gate</hi> in <hi>St. Katherines;</hi> which ſaid <hi>Riggs</hi> told him, this Examinant, That there would be a riſing of divers godly people in Arms for preſervation of Religion, about the time the Queen came to Town; and that they intended to ſeize the Kings Perſon about <hi>Camberwell,</hi> in his paſſage to ſee the Queen-mother at <hi>Greenwich:</hi> but after the Queen was come to Town, this Examinant asked the ſaid <hi>Riggs,</hi> why it was not done according to their intendment? who replyed, they were not then ready, becauſe the Congregational Churches and they were not fully agreed; but now they were come to an agreement, and the work would be done in a ſhort time; that all things were now near ready both in Countrey and City, and that a Frigat or more would revolt from the King to them. Not long after, the ſaid <hi>Riggs</hi> carried him, the ſaid <hi>Phillips,</hi> to the houſe of one <hi>Tonge,</hi> an old Army-Captain, but now a ſeller of Tobacco and Strong-water in <hi>Tower</hi>-ditch, where he heard <hi>Tonge</hi> ſay unto <hi>Riggs,</hi> that he had been at <hi>Windſor</hi>-Caſtle, and had made a Captain, two Serjeants, and a Gunner, to be of their Party; and that they had undertaken to deliver up the ſaid Caſtle to that Party which were now to riſe: to which <hi>Riggs</hi> replyed, You have done well. And further ſaid, I am now going to ſurprize two Caſtles in <hi>Kent;</hi> one of them, as this Deponent remembreth, was to be <hi>Deal</hi>-Caſtle; and this he would and could do, for that he had ſome correſpondence therein, and much acquaintance near, where he formerly uſed to preach. And further ſaith, That <hi>Tonge</hi> asked <hi>Riggs,</hi> who ſhould lead the men that were to riſe, and who command in chief? to which <hi>Riggs,</hi> reply'd, That <hi>Ludlow</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that work. He further ſaith, that he asked <hi>Riggs</hi> and <hi>Tonge,</hi> how this buſineſs might be carried on with ſafety and ſecreſie? <hi>Riggs</hi> told him, that there was a Council of Six which managed the Deſign, who ſat but one day in a place, and would not be ſpoken with, but by the Agitators of each County, who were employed by them to and fro in this work, to prepare and make ready all parties in the ſeveral Counties: and that theſe Six were of ſeveral Congregations and Opinions, to the end that all Parties might unite. And further ſaith, that one <hi>Wade,</hi> or ſome ſuch name, whom he heard <hi>Riggs</hi> and <hi>Tonge</hi> ſay was a Ship-chandler in <hi>Eaſt-Smithfield,</hi> did furniſh Powder to carry on this Deſign; in whoſe company he once was, and himſelf ſaid as much; which ſaid perſon he believes he knows when he ſeeth him again. He alſo ſaith, that <hi>Riggs</hi> told him all the Congregational Churches were now agreed to joyn in this Deſign. And that <hi>Riggs</hi> and <hi>Tonge</hi> deſired this Examinant to furniſh what Men and Arms he could; which he ſaith; he never intended to do, though he earneſtly requeſted it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96473:13"/> of him; only he ſaith, in ſome things he was too faulty, which he prayeth pardon for, which was, in ſending word to the ſeveral Meetings on Sunday laſt, That the Trained-bands were coming to ſeize them, upon which the chiefeſt of them made their eſcape before the Souldiers arrival: and that he being deluded by their fair Speeches, did promiſe to give them the Word when the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Riſing was to be; in which Riſing all the Churches aforeſaid promiſed to joyn, and the Fifth-Monarchy men to lead the Van. And further ſaith, that <hi>Riggs</hi> told him, they had a Declaration ready to fling among the people, againſt Biſhops and Common-prayer; and that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience was held forth therein: But firſt before this Declaration, they would ſeize on the Kings Perſon, and that then their Declaration would take with the people. And alſo ſaith, That one Captain <hi>Baker,</hi> one <hi>Bradley</hi> and <hi>Tonge</hi> were privy to all theſe tranſactions, which were debated by them in his preſence; and that the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> came afterwards to this Examinant, and diſcourſed all the aforeſaid particulars, and incited him to help on with the work; and told him, their Arms and Powder was diſtributed, and that a Porter, which was formerly a Souldier, carried the Powder to ſeveral places in a ſack. And further ſaith, that <hi>Riggs</hi> had told him, they had divers friends both in <hi>London</hi> and the Countrey, who had and would help them to Money; and that all their friends were now ready in all Counties, waiting only for the day when they were to Act; and that Treaſure in <hi>Guild-hall</hi> was likewiſe to be ſeized. And that the ſaid <hi>Riggs</hi> alſo told him, that they intended to ſurprize the <hi>Tower:</hi> which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap>d eaſily do, having ſome therein that would aſſiſt: and this was to be put in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution in ſome Evening, when Sir <hi>John Robinſon</hi> came home late, by following cloſe after his Coach with a Party of men which ſhould lie ready for that purpoſe.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>George Phillips.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> William Morrice, <hi>and Sir</hi> Henry Bennet, <hi>Principal Secretaries of State, Sworn.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>William Morrice.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I have had Intelligence, and ſeveral adverſtiſements from ſeveral parts of the Kingdom, that there was a Deſign of Riſing, and an Inſurrection; that it was the general expectation and common diſcourſe of the diſcontented and diſ-affected Party; nay, it was likewiſe preached about, that the Papiſts had a Deſign to Riſe and cut the Throats of the Proteſtants. I had four or five Letters to that effect ſent and brought me; and theſe Rumours were ſpread to excite others to joyn with theſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Henry Bennet.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Divers Letters of mine were to the ſame effect, that there was an Inſurrection intended at that time, and calling upon one another to be ready at that time.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> John Talbot <hi>Sworn.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>John Talbot.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe that the Evidences that I can give in relation to the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, is only the conſequences of this report, which they had rumoured about the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Maſſacring the Proteſtants; the conſequence was this, that it made a very great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance in <hi>Worceſterſhire</hi> and <hi>Warwickſhire;</hi> inſomuch that many Gentlemen that lived in the Countrey in very good repute, came under a very great ſuſpicion of all their Neighbours; and the Lieutenants wrote to one another to ſecure many: there was Guards ſet to ſatisfie the fears of the Countrey. Friday night which the Riſing ſhould have been on, they would not intruſt the Catholicks to be in Arms, but other Voluntiers.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> Sworn.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Hodges.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>In <hi>Dorſetſhire</hi> the 23 of <hi>October</hi> laſt, there was a Diſcovery made by ſome of the Town, of an intention of a general Riſing, and ſome of the Town were engaged in it: one Mr. <hi>Harvey,</hi> a Juſtice of the Peace examined divers perſons; four that were privy to it were ſent to the Gaol, and an Expreſs ſent to Secretary <hi>Morrice.</hi> Sir <hi>John Weld</hi> the younger gave ſuch an account of <hi>Shrewsbury.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, The occaſion of my going that Friday night was by Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> and Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> ſuggeſting the Papiſts Riſing. I was never known to be a Plotter, I had not gone forth that night, but only by their perſwaſions; I never heard of any Arms, but only the rumours of the people.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>I would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain know the Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> what number of Arms I told him was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not the number.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Major <hi>Thomas Bonfoy</hi> (at his deſire) was Sworn.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Major <hi>Bonfoy.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I do not remember that I ever ſaw <hi>Phillips</hi>'s face; but I did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it was his cuſtom to come to the <hi>Exchange</hi> to inſinuate himſelf into my Officers, making merry with them, and endeavouring to get the Word; and I believe it was his common practice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phillips.</speaker>
                  <p>He may remember I came on the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and ſpoke to him, and was look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for one of his Sergeants; I asked no man the Word, but preſently went to the <hi>Black Lyon</hi> in the new Alley, and from thence I went home: I did not ask the Word of any one. I have confeſſed before the Council, that at the beginning of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> I met Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> he then came and cloſed with me, and walking along ſaid he,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96473:14"/> Do not you hear of a riſing which ſhould have been on Friday? No, ſaid I: and then I I asked him where? he ſaid at <hi>Camberwel;</hi> and I thinking nothing of it, came home and ſpoke of it in my Family, as news from Mr. <hi>Riggs;</hi> on Tueſday I met Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> on <hi>Tower</hi>-hill, and he brought me to the houſe of Mr. <hi>Tong; Tong</hi> told <hi>Riggs</hi> he had been at <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> and made ſome party to ſecure the Caſtle; <hi>Riggs</hi> ſaid he could go down to <hi>Kent,</hi> and ſecure <hi>Deal</hi> and another Caſtle, for he had been a Preacher there. As for Mr. <hi>Tyler,</hi> one night coming neer Captain <hi>Foſters</hi> door, and having not ſeen him in three years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he asked me if I would not drink. I ſaid yes: then came in the Carryer of <hi>Norwich,</hi> I never ſaw this Carryer till then; then came Mr. <hi>Tyler,</hi> and there was talking of a Friggat, and the time of the lanching of it, and how it was to be man'd; but a little after Captain <hi>Foſter</hi> came and charged me with a report, that I ſhould ſay he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged; I told him I knew it not, nor ſaid it not; I have often declared I would have nothing to do in it, ti's true Mr. <hi>Roggs</hi> came and thanked me that I ſent notice to the meeting to be gone, and I told him I would do the people any good I could, but Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> knows I told him it was a dangerous buſineſs, and I would not meddle with it. I am ſure in the time of the Fifth-monarchy Inſurrection, I was faithful to the King, ventured my life as far as any man, Sir <hi>William Wale</hi> put truſt in me, and I did that ſervice there, that the Colonel himſelf did not venture to do: but that I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in this buſineſs, it is a trouble to me, and I hope the King will be merciful to me. I did not think that ſuch a thing would be diſcloſed in ſo ſhort a time, for my part I did not mind it, I knew nothing the night I was taken, I was in bed, and did not offer to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape. I hope the King will look upon me as one drawn in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I never had any meeting with any of the Council, moſt of the things I heard at Mr. <hi>Tonges</hi> houſe, meeting with Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> by chance; for thoſe Gentlemen Mr. <hi>Tyler</hi> ſpeaks of, the Council of Forty and of Six, I never knew them. I am ſorry I ſhould be concerned in ſuch diſcourſe, and I hope his Majeſty will have mercy on me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I was at a Neighbours houſe at that time, and went to drink a cup of Beer alone in their Kitchin, not knowing of <hi>Hill, Riggs,</hi> or <hi>Stubbs</hi> coming there, I never appointed them any meeting, they came in: and when they came in, they asked if there was not one <hi>Gibbs</hi> there, ſo the people of the houſe told them there was, they came and told me there was ſome Gentlemen would ſpeak with me, whereupon they being ſtrange faces, I ſtood up and ſaid, Gentlemen, what is your buſineſs with me? ſaid they, We would drink a Cup of Beer with you: then ſaid I, ſit down; they had a deſire to be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and to go up, whereupon not knowing their buſineſs, I went up, ſuppoſing they meant ſome matters of my trade, but we fitting down, Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> ſaid to me, Mr. <hi>Gibbs</hi> what is the beſt news? and Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> alſo did urge and ask for news: ſaid I, Gentlemen, I know no news, nor none I can tell you; ſo they made inquiry then for my Brother: ſaid I, I cannot tell where my Brother is, may be your buſineſs is moſt with him; I will ſend for him: and I ſent the Maid for him, and directed her, that if he was not at home, ſhe ſhould leave word for him to come: Again they urged for news, and I told them I knew none but only this, that the meeting was ſeized upon the laſt Sunday by armed Soldiers; but to tell them there would be any riſing, or of any arms delivered, or Piſtols, as Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> has related it, was a thing I was wholy ignorant of, I ſpeak as in the preſence of God, and I know I muſt one day give an account before the great Aſſizes of the world, and I fear that which they have ſaid, is out of ſome fear lying upon them, being guilty of ſome fact, and ſo to ſhroud themſelves under falſe lyes. They nor no other can prove that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I received or delivered any arms, or that any were delivered by my order; theſe men ſpeak falſly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>O. Bridgman.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>You miſtake your ſelf, they do not charge you with receiving or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering Arms, but you related it: your Brother ſpeaks ſuch things had been done, and if you know of this, and do conſent and conceal it, you are equally guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>After they had asked me the News, in a ſhort time my Brother came into the room, and I roſe from the Table, and went towards my Brother, and then my Brother aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me what thoſe Gentlemen were? I ſaid they were ſtrangers to me, and I knew not what they came for; ſaies he, they are ſtrangers to me alſo: immediately we aroſe, paid our reckoning, and went away: but that ever I ſaid my Brother told me, The Council of Six was broke up, all is ready, <hi>Ludlow</hi> to be General, and <hi>Alhallow.</hi> Eve the time, or that things went on well: I deny it, my Brother ſaid no ſuch thing to me, nor I to any man. When there was an Inſurrection by the <hi>Fifth-monarchy</hi>-men, I was then preſently ready at beat of Drum, went out in my own Perſon to ſerve his Maejſty at twelve a clock at night, though I had Servants of my own. My affections were ſuch, that I have always ever ſince his Majeſties Reſtauration been an obedient Subject to all his law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96473:14"/> Commands. I belonged then to Major <hi>Kilby</hi>'s Company, and did continue marching in the Company till the whole buſineſs was over, and ventured my Life, and never did contrive any Plot, or knew of any Plot, received or delivered any Arms. As to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bitants among whom I have lived many years, they have known my Converſation: I have been a peaceable Neighbour, ſubjecting my ſelf under the Government that now is, whom God continue. I deſire this Certificate may be read concerning my Neighbours teſtimony of my Converſation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>O. Bridgman.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>If you have any of them here they may ſpeak, but the Certificate cannot be read.</p>
                  <p>The Porters man of <hi>Bridewell</hi> ſaid he knew nothing but that he lived very quietly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Neighbours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>R. Foſter.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Nor I neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> what have you to ſay?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>I have nothing to ſay, but that the firſt man that brought me into this buſineſs was <hi>Tyler.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>All that I am charged with, is a report of the delivery of ſome Arms; ſeeing that a number of Arms are mentioned, I would ask what was the number?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riggs.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot well tell the number, but you ſaid there were ſome arms given, and ſome to be given; and that ſeveral had come to that place, and went away without Arms, and that within two or three days there would be more given; but as to the number I cannot remember.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>Now take notice of Mr. <hi>Hills</hi> Evidence, he hath aſſerted that there were 5 or 6 hundred, how do theſe agree? I can have ſufficient teſtimony of my Life and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>If you have any thing more to ſay in this buſineſs, ſpeak in the name of God, no body hinders you, but keep to the buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Saller.</speaker>
                  <p>I intreat the Bench to take notice what I am charged withal, it's only a report I received from one man, and told to another, and the very Original was a Lye, there was no ſuch matter, and yet here is audacious Evidence; he ſaies I named 5 or 600 and yet <hi>Riggs</hi> to whom I ſpoke heard me name no number</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Council.</speaker>
                  <p>One ſpeaks to the Arms, but does not remember the number; they both ſpeak to the thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>How can Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> be a competent Witneſs againſt me; when he never ſaw my face before, but ſaies Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> told him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Hill.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I ſaid not ſo, but that I heard it from your own mouth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Solicitor.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Riggs,</hi> why did you go to Mr. <hi>Sallers</hi> to help Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> to Arms?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Riggs.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe Mr. <hi>Sallers</hi> told me the day before that he heard there was ſome delivered, and more would be, and the next day we went to the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and there he told me this ſtory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot hear him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>O. Bridgman.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>He ſaies you told him the day before there was Arms delivered, and more would be delivered, and then the next day he and Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> came on the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and then you ſpoke thoſe words which they both witneſs againſt you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſpake no ſuch a word; It's true, what <hi>Wapſhot</hi> told me, I told <hi>Riggs,</hi> which was, That there were Arms delivered; but it ſeems there was none: and I told him I would tell him the truth the next day on the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and ſo in the mean time ſpeaking with <hi>Wapſhot,</hi> he told me there was no ſuch thing, and I told <hi>Riggs Wapſhot</hi> ſaid there was none.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray what made you ſo buſily enquire after Arms if you were not concerned?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>I did not enquire after it, but accidentally meeting him in <hi>Mark-Iane</hi> he told me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, as you are my Judge, ſo I hope you will be my Councellor; and I pray your advice whether Mr. <hi>Tyler</hi> and Mr. <hi>Riggs</hi> be competent witneſſes againſt me, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſame caſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>O. Bridgeman.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Where is the cauſe of your exception?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe they are in the ſame caſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>O. Bridgeman.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>There are four witneſſes all againſt you, your own confeſſion and examination againſt you; through the whole buſineſs you are a principal perſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs I did confeſs it in the <hi>Tower,</hi> being threatned with the Wrack.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>O. Bridgeman.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>There is Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> Mr. <hi>Riggs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bradley,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Tyler;</hi> there is <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Bradley</hi> without exception; <hi>Bradley</hi> he was not at all concerned, he went along with you to know what you ſaid; and Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> was not a perſon in the deſign, but made uſe of only to find out the Plot; they did nothing unjuſtifiable, ſo they are witneſſes without exception.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serjeant <hi>Glyn.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>We deſire your Lordſhip to declare whether <hi>Riggs</hi> and <hi>Tyler</hi> be lawful witneſſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:96473:15"/>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>O. Bridgem.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I would have you know this, whereas you make exception againſt thoſe perſons that are guilty of the ſame crime, that's a miſtake to ſay they are not witneſſes: in caſes of Treaſon, where there are works of darkneſs, theſe are things men will not do by day-light but in darkneſs, and who can diſcover theſe works of darkneſs better than they that have to do with them, if God turn their hearts? It's true, ſuch perſons as theſe are, if they had been convicted, they are not Witneſſes, but though they are in the ſame fault, it is frequent they are allowed: beſides, they are not witneſſes alone, there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers circumſtances, 1 <hi>Edward</hi> 6. 5 <hi>Edward</hi> 6. both Statutes ſay, there ſhall be two lawful witneſſes in caſes of High-Treaſon, that is, ſuch witneſs as the law would allow, before thoſe ſtatutes: the meaning of the ſtatutes was, that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> might not be taken upon a bare ſurmize; therefore the Law ſaies, There ſhall be two witneſſes. When one is accuſed of Treaſon, another in the ſame offence convicted and untainted, his Evidence is made uſe of, and though it is not ſo upright a witneſs as others, yet he is ſuch a witneſs as the Jury is to take notice of: it is plain by ſeveral circumſtances, you have been a principal perſon, a Leader on of the buſineſs; though a man be but preſent, when Treaſon is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or deſigned and acted, if this man be preſent and ſhew any thing of approbation, his concealing of it is as much Treaſon as he that did it s they are all principals in Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Hen. Finch.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhips and you Gentlemen of the Jury, you have heard the Evidence of the Priſoners at the Bar, five of them have ſtood out their Tryal, a ſixth hath confeſſed the Fact againſt thoſe perſons that now ſtand at the Bar; under good favour, there is a clear and unqueſtionable proof of the Crime charged of them, and they have not ſaid any thing that hath either taken away the credit of the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or excuſed the matter; if you conſider firſt <hi>Tonge,</hi> there is againſt him four wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and thoſe unqueſtionable, as you heard the direction of the Court, that he knew of the deſign, approved of it, contrived how to ſurprize <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle, had corrupted the head Gunner and Serjeant there, that he did contrive to ſeize <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and if you believe <hi>Bradly,</hi> adviſed as the fitteſt way, to break into Privy-Garden: all this againſt <hi>Tonge,</hi> with a world of other Evidence how active he has been, his houſe was the place of Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he imparts the deſign to <hi>Phillips,</hi> and <hi>Phillips</hi> undertakes to get the Word of the Trained-Bands. I think none can prove more than is proved againſt him. When you come to hear the proof againſt <hi>Phillips,</hi> it is proved that he offered to betray 300 Arms in the Artillery, where he had ſome kind of Truſt, and that he was ready to endeavour the Word when the Inſurrection was to be, and but a very little before, he is the man that diſcovers to the Congregational Meetings, that the Trained-Bands where coming to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize them, that is in his own confeſſion, as well as the willingneſs in him to diſcover the Word. It is proved that <hi>Tonge</hi> and <hi>Stubbs</hi> were preſent at thoſe diſcourſes touching ſurprizing the <hi>Tower,</hi> ſecuring the King, this is proved expreſly againſt them, <hi>Stubbs</hi> he thinks he has ſaid fairly for himſelf, when he doth ask Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> whether he did not ſay he had horſes and 200<hi>l.</hi> to carry on the work, Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſays he did ſay ſo, then it ſeems <hi>Stubbs</hi> was inquiſitive what helps there were to carry it on; Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> goes further, that in the preſence of <hi>Stubbs,</hi> it was ſaid there ſhould be no quarter given, but ſuch as <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> ſhould have if he were taken. When you come to <hi>Gibbs,</hi> he does deny all the whole matter, and indeed ſo they would all; and they have nothing to ſay, but to cry all the witneſſes have ſworn falſly, and God is a Righteous God, and he will require their blood one day; but remember what a horrid proteſtation was in that Letter that was ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to Alarm the whole Kingdom, as if a Maſſacre were intended by the Papiſts, and the Watch-word they ſhould all riſe by: that Letter ſaies, <hi>I call the Eternal God to witneſs, that this is no Trepan, but a ſober Truth.</hi> Do you think, that men who are not aſhamed to call the Eternal God to witneſs to a Lye, when 'tis to raiſe Sedition, will make any ſcruple at ſuch proteſtations at the Bar, when 'tis to ſave their lives? and if a man may ſcape by his own proteſtation, who ſhall ever be found guilty? But <hi>Gibbs</hi> thinks he ſays a great deal for himſelf, when he ſays his Neighbours can give great teſtimony of his good Converſation. Alas, who will deny to give a good report of a man till he hear evil proved againſt him? But do you think a little demure and ſober carriage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a mans Neighbours, will ſerve to ballance an Evidence of High-Treaſon? Is not the proof clear, that he did both know the Deſign, and approve it? Mark what <hi>Gibbs</hi> tells the company:</p>
                  <p>My brother, ſaith he, for his part he will not ſpeak before you; but if you be honeſt men, this is the News, that was ſpoke like one that was not conſenting to it; well then, what is the News? he tells them why the Council of Six are broke up, <hi>Friday</hi> is the day of Action, <hi>Ludlow</hi> is to be General. Can any man be privy to theſe things, and relate
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96473:15"/> them ſo cheerfully, and yet not be conſenting? believe it, it is a hard matter to find grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter evidence of a knowledge and conſent againſt any Conſpirator, until he break out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to open action. <hi>Sallers,</hi> he ſays that the Witneſſes do not agree: for Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſpeaks that he ſaid there was Five hundred Arms delivered, and Forty men went without Arms, but within two or three days there would be more: and when <hi>Riggs</hi> comes to ſpeak, he ſays, he did ſay Arms were delivered, and more would be, but he did not remember what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and becauſe they agree in the thing, but not in the number, therefore he thinks they diſagree in the matter. Obſerve what reaſon was there that <hi>Riggs</hi> comes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of <hi>Sallers</hi> for Arms, becauſe <hi>Sallers</hi> told him the day before Arms were delivered, and more would be, he thought therefore he came to a very proper perſon to tell him. If you mark, <hi>Sallers</hi> does deny openly in the Court that ever he ſaw the face of <hi>Hill</hi> till he was apprehended, although <hi>Hill</hi> was with <hi>Riggs</hi> when the Arms were ſpoken of upon the <hi>Exchange.</hi> And then he ſays again, that <hi>Hill</hi> ſpeaks by hear-ſay: he is out in that too; for Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> ſwears expreſly, he heard the words themſelves from <hi>Sallers.</hi> Then here are theſe before you, four witneſſes againſt <hi>Tonge,</hi> two againſt <hi>Phillips,</hi> and his own confeſſion; here is two againſt <hi>Gibbs,</hi> with theſe circumſtances, If you be honeſt men this is the news, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here are two Witneſſes likewiſe againſt <hi>Stubbs,</hi> who was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe preſent at all their Debates, even when the King himſelf was to have had the ſame quarter with <hi>Ludlow.</hi> Now Gentlemen, that there was a Conſpiracy, I think you have a clear Evidence: we may thank God, and the care of the King and his Miniſters, that it went no further; but 'tis no thanks to theſe men, they would have carried it to the extremity, had they had power; and with out queſtion this was formed by other kind of wits than theſe poor contemptible Agitators, who are now tryed for it. You ſee there was a Council of Forty, and an under-Council of Six, a Declaration framed to ſcatter at the time of Action, and that Action directed to be both in the City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, juſt in effect at the ſame pitch of time; and that it might be ſo, a wicked and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Letter is contrived, and many thouſand Copies diſperſed; and it wrought ſo far, that the Countries, much about the time appointed, were in great diſorder, as you have heard it proved. Is it not plain, that an evil ſpirit went throughout the whole Nation, and animated the whole party of Malecontents? moſt evidently it was a terrible Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy. Gentlemen, 'tis true, it is a queſtion of Blood, but 'tis Royal Blood, 'tis the Blood of Princes and Nobles, and it concerns the peace and ſecurity of the Kingdom, and every mans propriety, and of Religion, for they had left no man of Conſcience or Reputation behind, if they had prevailed. Conſider the Maſſacre theſe men would have committed, had they proſpered, and oppoſe that to the pretended Maſſacre, which they gave out by their Letter the Papiſts would have committed. Conſider that you have the life of the King in your hands, and I doubt not but he and the whole Kingdom ſhall always be ſafe in the Verdict of honeſt men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Robert Foſter.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>My Maſters of the Jury, I cannot ſpeak long to you; you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the nature of this buſineſs, ſuch as I think you have not had the like preſident in your time. My ſpeech will not give me leave to diſcourſe of it; for the Witneſſes, they are none but ſuch as may ſatisfy all honeſt men, it is clear they all agreed to ſubvert the Government, to deſtroy his Majeſty: what can you have more? two of the witneſſes are without exception, but I do not ſee any way but their teſtimony is good. For the parties, they in themſelves are very inconſiderable; theſe are but the out-boughs, and if ſuch fellows are not met withal, theſe kind of people are the fitteſt inſtruments to ſet up a <hi>Jack-ſtraw,</hi> and a <hi>Wat-Tyler;</hi> therefore you muſt lop off theſe, or elſe they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage others. You ſee one of their own company hath confeſſed the Fact out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of his own conſcience: But I leave the Evidence to you. Go together.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Officer was Sworn to keep the Jury.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Jury withdrawed, and after an hours Conſultation, the Jury returned.</p>
               <p>Silence was commanded, and <hi>James Hind</hi> fetcht from the Goal to the Bar.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, anſwer to your names. <hi>Edmund Butler, Clement Pung,</hi> and the reſt of the Jury before mentioned, are you all agreed of your Verdict?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>Who ſhall ſay for you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>The Foreman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>Set up <hi>Thomas Tonge</hi> to the Bar. <hi>Thomas Tonge</hi> hold up thy hand. Look upon him Maſters; how ſay you? is he guilty of the Treaſon whereof he ſtands Indicted, or not guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>Guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Look to him keeper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>What Goods and Chattels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>None.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>George Phillips</hi> to the Bar; How ſay you? is he guilty of the Treaſon whereof he ſtands indicted, or not guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96473:16"/>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>Guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Look to him keeper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>What goods and chattels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>None.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Francis Stubbs</hi> to the Bar; How ſay you? is he guilty of the high Treaſon whereof he ſtands indicted, or not guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>Guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Look to him Keeper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>What goods and chattels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>None.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Sallers</hi> to the Bar; How ſay you? is he guilty of the high Treaſon whereof he ſtands indicted, or not guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>Guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Look to him Keeper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>What goods and chattels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>None.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs</hi> to the Bar; How ſay you? is he guilty of the high Treaſon whereof he ſtands indicted, or not Guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>Guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Look to him Keeper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>What Goods and Chattels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>None.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>Hearken to your Verdict as the Court hath recorded it. You ſay that <hi>Thomas Tonge</hi> is guilty of the Treaſon whereof he ſtands Indicted, and ſo all the reſt. And you ſay, that they, nor any of them had any Goods or Chattels, Lands or Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at the time of committing the ſaid Treaſon, or at any time ſithence to your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and this you ſay all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jury.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Tonge</hi> hold up thy hand; thou haſt been Indicted of High-Treaſon, thou haſt thereunto pleaded Not guilty, and for thy Tryal haſt put thy ſelf upon God and the Countrey, and the Countrey hath found thee guilty; what haſt thou to ſay for thy ſelf, why the Court ſhould not proceed to judgment, and thereupon award execution of thee according to the Law?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tong.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray mercy from the King, I cry for mercy from the King.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Tye him up Executioner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>George Phillips</hi> hold up thy hand; thou art in the ſame caſe that <hi>Thomas Tonge</hi> is, what canſt thou ſay? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phillips</speaker>
                  <p>Kneeled down, and ſaid, I pray the mercy of the King and the Honourable Bench.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Tye him up Executioner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Francis Stubbs</hi> hold up thy hand; thou art in the ſame caſe the two laſt Priſoners before thee are, what can'ſt thou ſay? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stubbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I beg mercy, I was meerly drawn in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Tye him up Executioner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>John Sallers</hi> hold up thy hand; thou art, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what canſt thou ſay? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sallers.</speaker>
                  <p>I would intreat this Honourable Bench to conſider my condition, and what my charge is; I delivered no Arms: if I had known were they had been, I would have diſcovered them. I beg mercy from the King and this Honourable Bench.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Tye him up Executioner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs,</hi> hold up thy hand; thou art, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what canſt thou ſay? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>And pleaſe this Honourable Bench, I have ſomething to ſay. I am innocent as to my Conſcience of acting any thing Treaſonable againſt his Majeſty, the Lord forgive the Witneſs, I beg the mercy of the King.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Tye him up Executioner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of the Peace.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>James Hind</hi> hold up thy hand; Thou art guilty of the Treaſon whereof thou ſtandeſt indicted by thy own confeſſion, what canſt thou ſay? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hind.</speaker>
                  <p>I have nothing to ſay, but humbly beg the mercy of the King.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clerk of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Tye him up Executioner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cryer.</speaker>
                  <p>O Yes, my Lords the Kings Juſtices command all manner of perſons to keep ſilence while Judgement is in giving, upon pain of impriſonment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Robert Foſter.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Tong, George Phillips, Francis Stubbs, James Hind, John Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> and <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs,</hi> you ſix priſoners at the Bar, you have been here indicted for one of the greateſt crimes that can be committed upon earth, as to this world, againſt God, our King, and your Country, and againſt every good body that is in this land, for that capital ſin of High-Treaſon, which is a ſin inexpiable, &amp; indeed hath no equal ſin as to this world: upon this you have ſeverally been Arraigned, and have ſeverally (except one) pleaded Not guilty, and put your ſelves upon God and the Countrey for your Tryals, and your Countrey have found you guilty: for the five that are found guilty, I muſt ſay, that in you I find little remorſe, little ſenſe of your ſin; for the little man there, <hi>Hind,</hi> he hath much ſhewed his penitency. The manner and circumſtances of this, moſt men here believe, this did not originally ariſe from your particular ſelves, it muſt be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96473:16"/> put into you by ſome others. You ſpeak as if you deſired mercy; where was your mercy, that would have deſtroyed King and Country, and maſſacred many millions of ſouls, no reſpect of any perſon, but your own Fellows? I ſpeak this, that you may be the more ſenſible of your own Crime, that you may truly out of the remorſe of Conſcience, be ſorry for your ſin: you know very well the old councel, and it is a good one, <hi>Fear God, and honour the King, meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi> Medling with them that are given to change, has brought too much miſchief already to this Nation; and if you will commit the ſame ſin, you muſt receive the ſame puniſhment, for happy is he, that by other mens harms takes heed: I ſhall not ſpend long time with you, but if you will, as much as you can, diſcover the Actors herein, you will do God, the King, and your Country good ſervice. It remains that the Court proceed to Judgment, and therefore you ſix, the one by his own confeſſion, and other five by conviction of Law, the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Court is, That you be conveyed back to the place from whence you came, and from thence to be drawn upon an Hurdle to the Place of Execution, and there you ſhall be hanged by the neck, and being alive ſhall be cut down, and your privy-Members to be cut off, your Entrails to be taken out of your Body, and (you living) the ſame to be burnt before your eyes, and your head to be cut off, your body to be divided into four quarters; and your head and quarters to be diſpoſed of at the pleaſure of the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. And God have mercy upon your Souls.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="speeches">
               <head>The Confeſſion, Speeches, and Prayers, of <hi>George Phillips, Thomas Tonge, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel Gibbs,</hi> and <hi>Francis Stubbs,</hi> at the place of Execution, on <hi>Munday, Decemb. 22. 1662</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The manner of Conveying the Priſoners to the Place of Execution; and their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour there before they began to Speak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THe 22. <hi>Decemb. Thomas Tonge, George Phillips, Francis Stubbs,</hi> and <hi>Nathaniel Gibbs,</hi> were according to a late Sentence, drawn on two Hurdles, <hi>viz. Tonge</hi> and <hi>Phillips</hi> in one, and <hi>Stubbs</hi> and <hi>Gibbs</hi> in the other, to the common place of Execution at <hi>Tyburn:</hi> Where being come, they were received into a Cart under the Gallowes; and the Executioner deſiring them ſeverally to forgive him, they all declared they did freely forgive him and all their enemies, and did ſeverally ſalute each other with this Phraſe, <hi>Welcome Brother;</hi> and to one another ſaid, We are now launching into the deep. They being all tied up, <hi>Phillips</hi> gave the Executioner a ſmall ſum of Money, and the reſt directed the Executioner to take out of their pockets a ſmall parcel of money, as their gift to him; and <hi>Phillips</hi> afterwards bended a Six-pence, and preſented it to a friend of his, Mr. <hi>Stroud;</hi> and a Shilling likewiſe bended to one Mr. <hi>Clark.</hi> Then the Under-Sheriff of <hi>Middleſex</hi> acquainted them, they had all free liberty to ſpeak, provided they did not reflect upon his Majeſty or the preſent Government; which they all promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to do, and thanked him for his civility; and then <hi>Phillips</hi> began in manner fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing:
<floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Friends and Country-men,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I Am come this day to pay that great debt that I owe to Nature; it is a work that had need be well done, for it is but once to be done. My hope is now above: and for what I now come to ſuffer, for my own part, I bleſs God, in whoſe preſence I now ſpeak as a dying man, I had not any murderous thought againſt the King; but I have prayed for him, and wiſhed that he might Live and Reign, and long Reign in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and that God would make his Crown a Crown of Righteouſneſs upon his Head, and bleſs him in his Government, ſo that he may not know any of theſe occaſions more: For my part, I have ventured my life for his Majeſty; it was far from my heart to do any thing of that nature. The Lord receive my ſoul. I freely forgive all men, as I hope to be forgiven of God: I never did act any thing, but only this, which was my ignorance of the Laws, that I did not diſcover it; And I was juſtly found guilty for not diſcovering. I have done Mr. Sheriff; but hope, after my Brethren have ſpoken, we may have liberty to call upon the Lord.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-Sher.</speaker>
                  <p>It will not be denied you.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:96473:17"/>
               <p>Then Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> began in this manner:
<floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Friends and Countrey-men,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>YOu ſee me here a dying man: I have ſometimes been in ſome mens company, where I have heard them contriving the buſineſs for which I am condemned to die; and that which led me to joyn with them was this, I was and had been ſometimes in the Army; and I have looked upon this Cauſe to be good. As for his Majeſty, the Lord bleſs him, and proſper him, and put it into his heart, that he may be a Nurſing-Father in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to this Country.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-Sher.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you any more to ſay? you may ſpeak.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tonge.</speaker>
                  <p>I have nothing more.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>And then <hi>Gibbs</hi> proceeded and ſaid,</p>
               <sp>
                  <p>COuntry-men and Friends, and I hope Chriſtians, and the laſt conſideration is that that makes me the more free to ſpeak to you: we all profeſs to own God and Jeſus Chriſt to be our Saviour, our Redeemer, our Sanctifier, and giver of, and beſtower upon us E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life; this ſhould excite our Souls to love one another; and upon the account of Gods love, that God has ſo loved us, as to give Jeſus Chriſt to reconcile us ſinners to God, we ought to love one another; it is his great command. Truly as to the Cauſe for which I am brought here, God the great Judge of Heaven and Earth, before whom I ſtand, knows that in the place where I have lived, I behaved my ſelf as an obedient Subject, and when there was an Inſurrection by the <hi>Fifth-monarchy</hi>-men, I went out in my own perſon, though I had Servants as well as others, purely out of affection to his Majeſty, knowing that in the peace of his Government I ſhould have peace, and ſo I went out, hazarded my life, and continued out till all was quiet. I was at a Neighbours houſe drinking of a cup of Beer on Tueſday night in the Kitchin, alone, ſave only the man of the houſe and the maid; theſe men came in, one <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Riggs</hi> that are the witneſſes againſt me; there was <hi>Riggs</hi> and <hi>Hill,</hi> and this <hi>Stubbs,</hi> and one <hi>Beazely,</hi> and I being alone in the Kitchin, they asked for one <hi>Gibbs;</hi> the people of the houſe told me there were ſome Gentlemen would ſpeak with me, I wiſhed them to direct them to me, and they came to me; and through the ignorance of the Law, which it ſeems runs thus, If any words trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable againſt his Majeſty is ſpoken, it is Treaſon to conceal it. So thus I have given you in part the cauſe of my being here.</p>
                  <p>Hereupon information was given to the Kings Majeſty that I ſhould ſay there would be a Riſing, and that <hi>Alhallows</hi>-eve was the time; that there were Arms ſent into the Country, and that <hi>Ludlow</hi> was to be General; and this was charged upon me by the Kings Majeſty when I came before him to be examined: and upon <hi>Hills</hi> and <hi>Rigg</hi>'s Oath, I was ſent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and kept a long time a Priſoner, examined three or four times over by the Lords of his Majeſties Council. I have one word more, as touching my Judgment. I am reputed in the world to be one of thoſe that is called by the name of <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> a name of deriſion and ſcorn; One is an <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> one an <hi>Independant,</hi> one a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> one this, and one that, and one the other: who gave theſe nick-names to Chriſtians? There is but one God, one Lord Jeſus, one Baptiſm, one Hope of Glory: How comes the Body of Chriſt, or the Members of Chriſt to be called theſe nick-names? But now, as I am one that do profeſs Faith in God through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and do ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you all, and before the Lord, I know no other God, but the Eternal and Living God, that hath made the World, and that Rules and Reigns, and diſpoſes all his Creatures; I do believe in this God, he has been gracious to me a poor ſinner, and to all poor ſinners, that when we by reaſon of ſin had forfeited our mercies, and were under wrath and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting deſtruction, and muſt periſh for ever; that God did out of his rich grace and tender mercies give his only begotten Son, according to his promiſe, to be the bleſſing of God to the poor Gentiles, according as the Scripture did declare; the Scripture forſeeing that God would juſtifie the Heathens through Faith, preached before the Goſpel to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> ſaying, In thee ſhall all the Nations of the earth be bleſſed: he ſpeaks not of the natural ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but of Chriſt; ſo that all the bleſſings that God did convey to the ſinful world is by the means of Jeſus Chriſt, whom God in the fulneſs of time did ſend his Son born of a woman, to redeem poor ſinners under the Law: and herein was the great grace and mercy of God towards all ſinners, that he was ſo gracious to ſend his beloved Son out of his own boſom to take our natures upon him, who were defiled, and curſed, and condemned, and ſeparated from God. I ſay, Jeſus Chriſt took our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures upon him, and for this very end, to do the will of his heavenly Father: <hi>Lo it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the volume of thy book,</hi> I come to do thy will, O God, and it was his meat and drink
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96473:17"/> to do his will; and what was that, but that we might be ſanctified through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e offer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> up of the body of Jeſus Chriſt for our ſins, to tread the winepreſs of his Fathers wra and to endure the croſs, and bear all our ſins in his own body, that made his ſoul hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy unto death: he was a ſurety for us and our ſins, and for our ſakes the Lord laid on him the iniquity of us all and he hath born our grief and endured our puniſhment, it made his ſoul cry out, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? or elſe we muſt for ever be baniſhed out of the preſence of God, and never have any hopes of glory, of faith, or of ſalvation, had not the Son of God become our Mediator and Surety; ſo there is one God, and one Mediator, the Man Chriſt Jeſus. He gave himſelf a Ranſom for all our ſins, to free us from the wrath to come, everlaſting deſtruction, and from the worm that never dies. O that we could ever be thankful to God, live to him that hath ſo loved us, as to ſend his Son to die for us, and is by the almighty power of God raiſed from the dead, and now ſits at the right hand of God, and ever lives to make interceſſion.</p>
                  <p>Truly, friends, this is not the love of man, but the love of God, and therefore eternal love. God ſo loved the world; it is Gods love, he loved ſinners, ungodly ones; he did ſo love them as to give his only begotten Son to ſave them, to reconcile them, to uphold them, to redeem them from wrath to come: it was to ſeek and ſave them that were loſt. That is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners. We all like ſheep had gone aſtray, and muſt periſh in our ſins, had not the Lord Jeſus been ſent of his Father, out of his boſom to declare the good-will of God, and did it, by which we are ſanctified through the offering up of the body of Jeſus Chriſt; and this Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Eternal Son of God, he is the Mediator between God and poor ſinners. Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, ſaid Chriſt, and I will give you reſt; now this grace is from God, we are ſaved by grace, and that not of our ſelves, it is the gift of God, through faith in Chriſt we are ſaved, and all things that do pertain to life and godlineſs is the gift of God; now all things are of God, who hath reconciled us to himſelf by Jeſus Chriſt, to wit, that God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelf, not imputing their treſpaſſes unto him. Would you know the forgiveneſs of your ſins, your peace with God, and that God is well pleaſed, with you? God is reconciled by Jeſus Chriſt unto you, and does not impute your ſins unto you, but looks on the righteouſneſs of Chriſt as ſatisfaction, that thereby you might have the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of your ſins through the blood of Chriſt. Be it known unto all men, that through this mans preaching, the forgiveneſs of ſins. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.38, 39. and by him all that do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve are juſtified from all things, from which they could not be by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> now juſtification from ſin, and redemption from iniquity, is through the knowledge of Chriſts death for your ſins, and his reſurrection, and now there is no other name given under heaven whereby we can be ſaved, but by the name of Jeſus, and whoſoever believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his name ſhall not periſh, but have everlaſting life. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.24. It is the doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt, it is his word, and I hope you will ſearch the Scriptures, and look into thoſe things for your ſouls good, when Chriſt ſays, Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, He that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my words and believeth them, he hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but is paſſed from death to life. The reaſon why God does aſſure poor ſinners they ſhall not paſs into everlaſting condemnation and periſh, is through his rich grace, through his promiſes; for he hath promiſed he will be merciful to our iniquities, and our ſins will remember no more; and theſe his promiſes of grace which are all Yea and Amen in Chriſt, are ratified by the blood of Chriſt; the blood of Chriſt is the blood of the New Covenant, and it is that by which we have the forgiveneſs, remiſſion and cleanſing of all our ſins.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſheriff.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Gibbs,</hi> let me interrupt you, this is very good and pertinent, but you have ſaid theſe things over and over, there is another of your friends is to ſpeak, and the time grows ſhort, pray go on to the matter, or conclude.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall ſpeak a word or two as to the knowledge of forgiveneſs of ſins, by and through Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo the knowledge of the Reſurrection of the dead, it is the fruit of Jeſus Chriſt; for by the firſt man came death, and by the ſecond man Chriſt came life, and God that has by his exceeding great and mighty power, raiſed up Jeſus Chriſt from the grave and power of ſin, he alſo ſhall raiſe us up by the ſame power, and when he comes again the ſecond time, at his appearing and coming, we ſhall ſee him, and be made like to him, and he will receive us to himſelf; he is gone to prepare a place for us, and in his Fathers houſe are many Manſions; and if it were not ſo, he would have told us. And now God that hath given eternal life, and forgiveneſs of ſins unto his poor ſervants, he will alſo, when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come to judge the world, receive him into his everlaſting glory, which is my Faith expectation and hope, in God through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. A man may bear his infirmities, but a wounded Conſcience who can bear? When God ſmites, who can bear? and therefore I deſire, as I believe the forgiveneſs of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96473:18"/> all my ſins, through the rich grace of God, through the bloodſhed of Jeſus Chriſt his Son; every one muſt give account to God, and as their works are, ſo will their reward be; either accepted by God, as workers of Chriſt, or condemned as workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Laſt of all, as to the ſeparated Congregations to whom I belong, I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in thoſe few days that I have lived, there is a great deal of animoſity, evil will, hard cenſuring, and abuſing the precious Saints of Jeſus Chriſt. If they are in an error, you that are in the truth inſtruct them, and you may recover them out of the claws of the Devil: Are you Chriſtians, and have the light of God in your Souls? O then ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en your Brethren, do not give them nick-names, and abuſe them; that's not the way, Chriſt teaches another leſſon, <hi>That if thine enemy hunger you ſhall feed them, and if he be thirſty give him drink;</hi> we ſhould pray to the Lord that he would turn thoſe that be out of his way, into the right way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſheriff.</speaker>
                  <p>You know we muſt be all ſubject to Government, every Congregation muſt not have a Ruler; their Meetings are prohibited by good Authority, and becauſe they will not be obedient to good Government.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not ſay, that every Congregation muſt have a Ruler, and I hope I ſpeak the words of ſobriety; I hope you will put a charitable conſtruction upon what I ſay. As to the Magiſtrates I have a word or two.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſheriff.</speaker>
                  <p>Speak well of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gibbs.</speaker>
                  <p>Be not afraid, I will not ſpeak any evil of them; Magiſtracy is an Ordinance of God, and the end of Magiſtracy, is for the puniſhment of evil-doers, and the praiſe of them that do well; and for this purpoſe; I do deſire that the Lord will give to the ſupreme Magiſtrate here on earth, wiſdom and underſtanding, a wiſe Council, a Council fearing God, and hating covetouſneſs, that they may ſtudy to exalt the Throne of the King in righteouſneſs and truth O that we may all praiſe the Lord for deliverance out of condemnation; and I ſay it is the duty of all the Subjects of the Kings Majeſty, in all his Kingdoms and Dominions to live peaceably, and to pray for the Kings Majeſty: Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and interceſſions ought to be made for all men, eſpecially for Kings and Governours, for this very end, and purpoſe, that thereby we may live in all quietneſs, godlineſs, hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and juſtice; and to this very end the Lord bleſs our Magiſtracy, give them Counſel and Wiſdom, that they may love them that love the Lord, and hate them that hate the Lord.</p>
                  <p>After <hi>Gibbs</hi> had done ſpeaking, then <hi>Stubbs</hi> began, who went over all the particulars of his Tryal at large, to which for brevities ſake we refer you, only ſaith he, as followeth,
<floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
                        <body>
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Friends and Country-men,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>IT is true, and I muſt confeſs my ſin in the preſence of God, (and did ask mercy of the King) that I was in the company when I did hear wicked and Treaſonable words ſpoken, and I being ignorant, and not knowing the Law, did not diſcover what I did hear.</p>
                           <p>As to my Judgment, truly I deſire to own what the Scriptures own; I ſhall ſpeak of that place in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> which is the command of Chriſt, I deſire the Churches and people, every one to live the life of Faith, and love one another, I am confident it would be a means of abundance of comfort here in the Nation; there is a kind of heart-burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and riſing one againſt another; you are ſo and ſo, throw dirt one againſt the other; it is our and your duty, ſtill to be ſtudying to live in love, and bear with one another, not be angry, deſtroy, and fight one with another: O that we might live that life of love that God has commanded, then we may expect the preſence of God to be with us; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God hath a great Judgment againſt his own people for not loving one another.</p>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phillips.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. Sheriff,</p>
                  <p>I Have only one word to ſpeak before I go to my Prayers; that is, Here I ſee ſome Gentlemen preſent that are in the capacity that I was in, as a Souldier; I ſay, be faithful to your truſt, and beg of God that you may ſtand faſt, and not diſhonour God, nor be diſobedient to the King; when the Fifth-monarchy-men were up, I was free and willing to lay down my life for the intereſt of the Nation; and did venture as much as any young man in <hi>London:</hi> Therefore good friends, have a care, I am now brought to ſuffer; it is true I was guilty of concealing it, I deſire your Prayers, that now as we are going to the State of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, from whence there is no redemption; I humbly beſeech you, as Chriſtians and friends, that you would ſeek earneſtly to God, that now he may receive our ſouls into everlaſting reſt and happineſs, which he has been pleaſed to beſtow on them that love him and fear him; and the Lord knows my heart, I ſpeak it in his preſence, that had the King been pleaſed to ſhew mercy to me, I ſhould have been a faithful and true Subject to him all my days: but ſeeing it is the righteous hand of God that now I am come to this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death, I deſire you to lift up your Hearts and Souls to God with me, that when my ſoul ſhall leave this body, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt may with his everlaſting arms receive me to glory. There is no redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after death, we ſhall either go to eternal woe or eternal happineſs; therefore good friends, I deſire you to look up to God, that when my Soul departs, it may be received to glory.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>[Mr. <hi>Phillips</hi> his Prayer.]</p>
               <sp>
                  <p>O Eternal Lord God, thou that art the great Creator of Mankind, and thou that formedſt him in the womb, hear thy poor and ſinful creature, now he is coming to make his laſt approaches to thy Throne. O that thou wouldſt be pleaſed to look down in mercy upon my Soul: O Lord that thou wouldſt be pleaſed now to take my ſoul and waſh it, and hath it in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, who hath died and riſen again for me. O that now I could ſee the heavens opened, and Jeſus Chriſt ready to receive my ſoul. Be pleaſed, O Lord, to look upon me in thy tender mercy and compaſſion, and as thou haſt ſaid, thou doſt not delight in the death of a ſinner, therefore good Lord, look down upon my poor ſoul, and receive me into the everlaſting manſions which Jeſus Chriſt is gone before to prepare for all them that love thee.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96473:18"/> O Lord, we are now going, I hope, to an eſtate of happineſs, where we ſhall ſin and ſorrow no more, but where we ſhall ever reign with Jeſus Chriſt, O Lord, had we not ſome hopes, had we not ſome ſight of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt made known to our ſouls, we durſt not appear before thee this day, we durſt not ſtand before thee in thy preſence: O that thou wouldeſt more and more manifeſt thy gracious preſence with me; that thou wouldeſt uphold me to take the bitter cup and drink it freely. O Lord, I deſire to come unto thee; I have been a great ſinner before thee, but Jeſus Chriſt has died, is riſen, and is now at the right hand of his Father, making interceſſion for us. And good Lord, as thou haſt commanded us to come unto thee, and to believe in thee, and haſt ſaid, thou wilt in no wiſe caſt off the ſoul that comes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, in confidence of that hope, I deſire to fix my ſoul upon thee before I go hence, and be no more. Bow down the heavens, O Lord, and hear the requeſt of the poor ſoul before thee; and I beſeech thee for Chriſt his ſake, as thou wouldſt forgive me, ſo freely forgive all that have done evil againſt me. Be pleaſed to let the Kings Majeſty reign in righteouſneſs and holineſs put a ſpirit of power and might in his ſoul; and let him ſee wherein the ſtability of his Crown lies, in following Righteouſneſs and Juſtice and Judgment, and preſerving of that Truth that is made known to him out of the book of the Lord. Come down, Lord, to his ſoul, and let him ſee wherein is his hope, and O that he may at laſt li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and reign with Jeſus Chriſt for evermore. Good Lord look upon me, I am coming unto thee, theſe are my laſt words. O that thou wouldeſt be pleaſed to receive us this day, that we may dine with thee in Paradiſe; make known thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting kindneſs to my ſoul before I go hence and be no more, that I may receive that comfort and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which I have longed and looked for. Lord my hope is in thee thou wilt not fail them that put their truſt in thee, in thee is my truſt and confidence; if I periſh, I will periſh at the feet of Jeſus Chriſt. O that thou wouldſt humble me, and ſeal up the pardon of my ſins before I go hence, and let thy Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt manifeſt his gracious preſence with me, and cloath me with that wedding garment of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and then take me into his arms, and preſent me to his Father. O that thou wouldeſt be pleaſed to ſtrengthen and uphold me under this great ſtroke which thou haſt been pleaſed to inflict upon me; I kiſs the rod, and receive it thankfully from thy hand. I had been undone to all eternity, hadſt thou not afflicted me, bleſſed be thy Name, that thou haſt been pleaſed to ſend Jeſus Chriſt, upon him I depend, upon him I caſt my confidence, who is the rock of ages, and never failed any that came to him. Hear me and anſwer me, do for me and all thy Churches and people abundantly above what I can ask or think, and all for the ſake of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with thy ſelf and thy holy Spirit be all honour power, and praiſe, henceforth and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>[Mr. <hi>Tonge</hi> his Prayer.]</p>
               <sp>
                  <p>O Moſt Glorious, and Eternal Lord God, thou that haſt created the heavens and the earth, and formedſt of duſt us thy poor creatures, to which we are now returning. Lord I beſeech thee ſpeak peace to my poor ſoul, lift up the light of thy countenance upon me, and let me ſee in thee, and through faith in thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt, that I am in covenant with thee, and reconciled with thee. Holy Lord, I beſeech thee, let me ſee thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt ſitting at thy right hand reconciling of me to thy ſelf. Let me find my ſoul waſhed in the blood of the Covenant of thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt. Seal a pardon to me thy poor creature; O Lord, one ſmile of thy countenance is worth all the world; bleſſed be thy Name that thou haſt ſupported me hitherto. Lord God I beſeech thee finiſh thy good work thou haſt begun in me, and go along with me, and ſtrengthen and hold me to drink off this bitter cup. Be with me to the end. Remember the Governours of this Nation. O that thou wouldeſt ſhowr down upon the King and Council thy mercies, as thou ſhowreſt down rain on the ground, that they may rule for thee, and thoſe that fear thy Name may live in happineſs and peace under thee, for the ſake of thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt. O Lord, we pray thee remember all thy people, and be good to them, and deliver them out of their troubles, and ſpeak peace to them, and let them know thou wilt deliver them. Keep me to the end, and uphold me by thy right hand, and ſo receve me with joy, for the ſake of thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be all honour and power henceforward and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Gibbs</hi> his Prayer.</p>
               <sp>
                  <p>O Eternal, Everliving and Everloving God, who art a reconciled and loving Father unto thy poor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Creatures before thee, and unto all the children whom thou haſt called to believe in thee. O Lord, this is no ſmall priviledge, that ſinful duſt and aſhes mortal worms, ſhould have to do and to deal with ſo holy and infinite a God, as thou art, to make requeſts unto thee, conſidering the vaſt diſproporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that there is between thee, and poor ſinners: Thou art of purer eyes than to behold any unclean thing in thy preſence, O Lord. We our ſelves are nothing but polluted rags, and fountains of uncleanneſs, from the crown of the head to the ſole of the foot; all the faculties of the ſoul, and members of the body, are all members of unrighteouſneſs. Were it not therefore, that thou haſt been pleaſed to give us good hopes, and found out a way to hold communion with us, which is through the Lord Jeſus, in whom thou are well pleaſed, in whom thou haſt ſpoke forgiveneſs of ſins to our ſouls, we durſt not now ſtand before thee: but thou haſt promiſed, that though our ſins are as ſcarlet, thou wilt make them as white as ſnow; and though they be as crimſon, thou wilt make them as wool. Thou haſt opened a fountain of free grace, and eternal mercy for poor ſinners; that through the blood of the Lord Jeſus they may receive remiſſion, forgiveneſs, cleanſing and purging from all their ſins. Thou haſt laid an All-ſufficient help upon him, who is able to ſave to the uttermoſt, all that come to God by him. We have nothing of our ſelves to bring unto God, but ſins to pardon, and unclean ſouls to purge: Thou haſt been pleaſed to give thy Son, and together with him, freely to give us all things: Thou haſt given thy poor ſervant before thee, ſaith that has brought ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to his ſoul: Thou haſt ſaved him by thy free-grace; not of works, but through the mercies and blood of Jeſus Chriſt; and haſt ſprinkled the virtue of the blood of Chriſt in his conſcience, in the belief of the truth, as it is in Jeſus. O bleſſed be thy Name, that ſent him to ſeek, and to ſave us from condemnation; who is riſen with healing in his wings, and haſt ſet Chriſt before us, that we ſhould behold him that our ſins have pierced. Certainly great was that diſeaſe that needed ſuch a medicine; that nothing could expiate &amp; take away our ſins, and blot out the hand-writing that was againſt us, but the precious blood of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as of a Lamb without ſpot; he is now become our peace, who has made peace for us, through the blood of that his Croſs, and has made twain, one in himſelf, Jew and Gentile. He was delivered up for our offences, and roſe again for our juſtification: We in the knowledge of him, being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And bleſſed be thy Name, O merciful God, that has made ſuch a Covenant of everlaſting grace to poor ſinners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the children that do believe in thee, through Jeſus Chriſt. Thou haſt ſaid, thou wilt be merciful to all our iniquities and ſins, and wilt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them no more: Theſe are thy promiſes, and they are Yea and Amen Chriſt in Jeſus. Thou haſt made thy ſervant to hear thy voice in thy Son: Thou haſt been a merciful God to him, and forgiven him all his ſins, and juſtified him freely through the reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Who ſhall condemn us, or lay any thing to our Charge? It is God that juſtifies, who gave himſelf a ranſom for our ſins, is riſen again, and now ſits at the right Hand of God, ever living and making interceſſion for us; whoſe blood
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96473:19"/> ſpeaks better things than the blood of <hi>Abel:</hi> His blood cryed for vengeance, but the blood of Chriſt cries for peace and forgiveneſs. God is in Chriſt reconciling himſelf unto the world, not imputing their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes: He hath made him to be ſin for us, who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God in him. Bleſſed be thy Name, that thou haſt ſent thy holy Child Jeſus, to be the propitiation, not only for our ſins, but for the ſins of the whole world. He hath ſuffered the juſt for the unjuſt, that he might bring us unto God. O do thou therefore help thy poor ſervants before thee, and all thy children: Give us to ſee the removal of eternal death, by the death of the Lord Jeſus. Let us ſee thee at peace with us, and juſtifying of us, through thy grace. All have ſinned, and come ſhort of thy glory; but being juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied through the redemption of Chriſt Jeſus, whom God hath ſet forth to be a propitiation for the ſins of the whole world. Thou haſt promiſed, that whoſoever believeth in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thy grace, thy mercy, thy love ſhall not periſh, but have everlaſting life; and thou haſt given to thy poor ſervant excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great and precious promiſes, and by thy own ſpirit, bringing home theſe promiſes, given him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Records thou haſt given of thy Son; which beareth witneſs, that God is reconciled to him, and well pleaſed with him in Chriſt Jeſus, and given him eternal life. And ſeeing thou haſt bid his ſoul in Jeſus Chriſt, when he ſhall appear, then ſhall we appear with him in glory, and be made like to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: By the ſame power that thou raiſeſt up Jeſus Chriſt from the dead, by the ſame power thou art able to ſubdue all things. There is nothing impoſſible with God; what ever thou haſt promiſed, ſhall be performed; Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but one title of thy word ſhall not fail: And therefore bleſſed be thy Name, that thou haſt revealed theſe things to thy poor and unworthy Creature; that thou art his God and Father; that thou wilt never leave him, nor forſake him; and thou haſt hid his life in Chriſt, and wrote his name in the Book of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and he rejoyceth that he knows he is his, who is the onely true God: Knows thou art well pleaſed with him, and juſtified him freely from all his ſins, accepted him, in and through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. O therefore, dear Father, do thou receive his ſoul according to thy promiſe, that he may be thine, and thou his God. O bleſſed Father, do thou be pleaſed to do good to all thy people: And now, dear Father, take care of our families, be thou a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to our yoke-fellows, a Father to the Fatherleſs: Do them good abundantly above what we are able to ask or think; and what is wanting, and loſt by our removal do thou hand out to them, thy mercy and grace, and move the hearts of the children of men to do them good: Be thou their God, help them, and provide for them: Seal up thy loving kindneſs to them, not only for this life, but for the life to come.</p>
                  <p>Do good to our Magiſtrates; thou who haſt the hearts of all men, make ſuch as are about them, men fearing God, and hating covetouſneſs, that may judge for God, that he may have glory. O be pleaſed to let his Majeſty Rule and Reign in righteouſneſs; let his Throne be eſtabliſhed in Righteouſneſs, and reveal the choiceſt of thy bleſſings to His poor ſoul: manifeſt Chriſt Jeſus, and him crucified to him; and give Him to ſee the moſt precious blood of Chriſt, cleanſing him from all ſins. Bind up his ſoul in the bundle of everlaſting life: Crown Him with a Crown of Righteouſneſs, as well as with an earthly Crown: Let him be a Nurſing Father, and Nurſing Mother indeed, to this Nation; that He may hate the evil door, and be a praiſe to them that do well. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> good to every one of us; O help us that we may firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God. Firſt, believe in God, and then honour our King: Firſt, fear God and ſerve him, and then give to Ceſar, that which is Ceſars. Give unto the King, that which is the Kings; Give Him all obedience to live quietly in all godlineſs and honeſty: And now, O Lord, do thou take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that ſpirit of emulation and ſtrife, and malice. From whence comes wars? come they not from our luſts? The Lord remove pride, preiudice, and malice from us, and cauſe us to love one another: The Lord teach every one in their places, to walk continually, to the glory and praiſe of God; that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the name of Chriſtians, may be enabled to walk humbly and meekly; to do good, to walk uprightly, and to love mercy, and then certainly we may expect that bleſſing that God hath promiſed to them that believe in him, which is eternal life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>[Mr. <hi>Stubb's</hi> Prayer.]</p>
               <sp>
                  <p>PRecious and eternal Lord God, in thy preſence, O Lord, are we, and in the preſence of thy Son, and of thy holy Angels, and in the preſence of the great multitude that now is beholding us poor objects, poor worms, poor duſt and aſhes; and truly, Lord, we were not able to lift up our heads this day, except thou didſt come in by thy mighty Power. O Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elp us to ſee the Heavens opened this day; and that the Arms of our Chriſt may be opened to receive our poor ſouls. O Lord, we are bidding farewel to the world, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> enjoyments; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to every thing and now, Lord, we are going home to thy dear and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> forth our ſouls, and enlarge our hearts after thee, that we may be in purſuit of our God; our ſouls long for the Lord, as the Hart longs or pant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> after the water brooke. Lord appear in this hour; this is a great Tryal, that thy poor creatures are brought to. Now come and ſmile upon thy poor worms: O that thou wouldeſt communicate thy ſelf unto us; the Lord lift up the light of his countenance upon our precious ſouls, be a precious God to us, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Father; thou haſt not left poor ſouls in the dark, in ſuch an hour as this; O that thou wouldſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municately thy ſelf unto us; we are now departing and dying, good Father, we pray thee, that we may have the ſpiritual life communicated to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Look in mercy upon every heart here in thy preſence; O that their ſouls may be ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: thou haſt given Chriſt to dye for us, whilſt creatures here; thy blood is able to waſh and make me clean; O there is no ſpot, no dye, but the blood of Jeſus is able to take it away. O Lord help us, that we may dye in the love of Jeſus Chriſt: And good Lord, we deſire that thou wouldſt look in mercy upon him that in the Officer &amp; Execution of thoſe poor worms; and as he is to waſh his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> our blood, O Lord waſh his Soul in the blood of the Lamb of God. Father, thou knoweſt we deſire the good of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oul: we forgive him, and we deſire to forgive every one. And dear Lord, we deſire thee to look upon the King communicate the riches of thy mercy unto his Majeſty; we deſire his Soul may be ſaved; thou haſt the hearts of all Kings in thy hand, draw forth his heart, that he may love thoſe things that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee, and love them that thou loveſt; let him be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs, and let Juſtice and Judgment run down the ſtreets of <hi>England</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a mighty ſtream. We pray thee to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> forth our Souls to pray for every Relation; beget love in all ſorts of people, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> they may live the life of love, that when they depart this life, they may enjoy the bleſſed Comforter, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And dear Lord, thou or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to give us a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſt of thy love this day; Lord thou haſt given us a pardon, bleſſed be thy Majeſty for it; thou haſt given us a reprieve for our Souls, we are delivered from death to life; we hope when we depart this world, we ſhall enjoy thoſe bleſſed man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ons to all eternity. And gracious Father, we deſire to bleſs thee, for that civility we have had from thoſe that have been Officers here; Lord make it up to them; and we deſire to bleſs thee for it. O the riches, and the height of the grace of God, and the love of Jeſus Chriſt to poor ſinners! We may ſee that thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be pleaſed to look in mercy upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> poor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>; O that thou wouldſt unite their hearts in love together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O that there might not be any more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> or lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed: unite their hearts in love and obedience, that they may fear God, honour the King, that they may deſire in all righteouſneſs and holi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt, to do thoſe things that are according to thy mind and will. And gracious Father, thou canſt not abide Hypocrites, the Lord cauſe Souls to love holineſs, and the power of godlineſs, that they may not ſhrowd themſelves under the profeſſion, when there is no reality. Look in mercy upon all the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, communicate thy mercy and love to them; be pleaſed to be with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this day, and go along with us. O that we may bleſs that with our Souls, and all that is within us. Be with us, and do for us, more than we are able to ask or think, upon the account of Jeſus Chriſt, in whom thou art well pleaſed, to whom be all praiſe and glory now and for ever. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>After which, their Caps being ſeverally pulled over their faces, and after ſome private Ejaculations, the Executioner cauſed the Cart to be drawn away; and after they had hanged a while, they were ſeverally Headed and Quartered, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Sentence, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Heads and Quarters conveyed in a Basket to <hi>Newgate,</hi> to be diſpoſed of at the Kings pleaſure. Which he was graciouſly pleaſed thus to diſpoſe of; Their ſeveral Quarters to be Buried, which was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly done on Saturday-night, <hi>December</hi> 27. Their Heads to be ſet on ſeveral Poles, Two on the one <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> and two on the other, as neer the <hi>Tower</hi> as may be.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96473:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
